<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sick-bed thoughts, upon those words of the apostle in Phil. 1, 23  ... Part. I containing an answer to that great and solemn question, what that state and condition is, which a person must be found in, before he can have good and sufficient ground, not to be affraid,  or unwilling to dye? / by J.B.</title>
            <author>Batchiler, John, ca. 1615-1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 167 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76092</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B1075</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42879</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875888</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875888</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152194</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76092)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152194)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2283:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sick-bed thoughts, upon those words of the apostle in Phil. 1, 23  ... Part. I containing an answer to that great and solemn question, what that state and condition is, which a person must be found in, before he can have good and sufficient ground, not to be affraid,  or unwilling to dye? / by J.B.</title>
                  <author>Batchiler, John, ca. 1615-1674.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 132 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the Year, 1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Error in paging: p. 106 numbered 105.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, and with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Death --  Religious aspects --  Christianity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152194:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SICK-BED Thoughts, Upon thoſe words of the Apoſtle, In Phil. 1.23.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Having a deſire to depart, and to be with Chriſt, which is far better.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>PART. I.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Containing an ANSWER TO That <hi>great</hi> and <hi>ſolemn</hi> QUESTION, What that <hi>State</hi> and Condition is, which a Perſon muſt be found in, before he can have <hi>good</hi> and <hi>ſufficient ground,</hi> not to be <hi>affraid,</hi> or <hi>unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> to Dye?</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1667.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:152194:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152194:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHilſt all the World is in an <hi>hurry,</hi> toſſed here and there with <hi>vanity</hi> and <hi>vexation,</hi> whilſt <hi>few</hi> or <hi>none</hi> almoſt, are looking after their <hi>future</hi> ſtate, or <hi>regarding</hi> what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of them to <hi>Eternity;</hi> I judged it not amiſs, a little to <hi>call thee aſide</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch <hi>ſerious</hi> thoughts, as it pleaſed the Lord <hi>lately</hi> to caſt into mine <hi>own</hi> heart, whilſt I paſſed away ſome <hi>reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs</hi> nights on my <hi>Sick-Bed.</hi> If thou ſhalt vouchſafe to read them over, with a <hi>candid</hi> minde, and an <hi>honeſt</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, I hope thou wilt not think thy time <hi>loſt,</hi> nor bee unwilling that two or three <hi>peeces</hi> more, much about the ſame <hi>bulk</hi> and <hi>price,</hi> ſhould follow this their <hi>fore-runner,</hi> to <hi>compleat</hi> what I propound, if the Lord ſpare life and
<pb facs="tcp:152194:3"/>health, <hi>farther</hi> to handle; <hi>viz.</hi> An Anſwer to a <hi>ſecond</hi> great and ſolemn Queſtion, <hi>What ſtate of Grace a perſon muſt arrive at, before he can truly ſay with the Apoſtle</hi> Paul, <hi>that he hath a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement deſire to depart and to be with Chriſt?</hi> This will make up <hi>another</hi> lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Treatiſe of its ſelf. The next to which, will bee an Anſwer to a <hi>third</hi> Queſtion, <hi>viz. What posture and frame of heart, a perſon muſt be found in, that can truely ſay, he is fit and ready to Dye?</hi> that can ſay with good old <hi>Simeon, Now let thy ſervant depart in peace:</hi> To which will bee <hi>ſubjoyn'd,</hi> a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, to prove that a <hi>righteous mans death, is no other than a going to Chriſt.</hi> This will make a <hi>third</hi> Treatiſe. Laſtly, the enquiring into the <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> why a <hi>good</hi> man ſhould, and will by all means, <hi>deſire to bee with Chriſt,</hi> and that as <hi>ſoon</hi> as <hi>poſsibly</hi> may be (let his condition here in this World, bee <hi>never ſo pleaſing</hi> to fleſh and blood) will make up the <hi>fourth</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:152194:3"/>part, and ſo finiſh the <hi>whole</hi> deſign: That which this <hi>laſt</hi> Diſcourſe will be founded upon, will be thoſe words, <hi>Which is far better.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now if any ſhould ask, <hi>why</hi> I chuſe <hi>this</hi> Subject of all others, to write upon, at <hi>this</hi> time? I anſwer, not onely becauſe the <hi>Lord</hi> caſt it <hi>ſtrongly</hi> into my minde, at a <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> when I knew not but that I might <hi>leave</hi> the world, and ſo was willing to be <hi>preparing</hi> for my change; but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo becauſe <hi>all things</hi> here below, ſeem to have a <hi>face</hi> of <hi>death</hi> upon them; as in all places, ſo <hi>moſt of all</hi> in this our poor <hi>ruinated</hi> City of <hi>London;</hi> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the <hi>wonderful</hi> deſolation of the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> thereof, by the <hi>late raging Peſtilence,</hi> even <hi>beyond</hi> what hath been known in any former age; and the late <hi>ſcattering, impoveriſhing,</hi> and almoſt <hi>ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> undoing of many <hi>thouſands</hi> more, in the <hi>loſs</hi> of their <hi>eſtates, trades,</hi> and other outward <hi>comforts</hi> and <hi>enjoyments,</hi> and this <hi>all England over,</hi> more or leſs: I
<pb facs="tcp:152194:4"/>ſay, beſides all this, hath not the <hi>wrath</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>men,</hi> as 'twere, <hi>joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> in one, to lay the very <hi>houſes</hi> alſo, and the <hi>habitations</hi> deſolate; and to make them likewiſe <hi>feel,</hi> ſuch a <hi>ſtroke of death and diſſolution,</hi> as they were <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way</hi> capable of receiving? Oh! <hi>where,</hi> under the <hi>whole</hi> heavens, is ſuch another <hi>woful ſpectacle</hi> to bee ſeen! ſuch an <hi>angry mark</hi> of divine diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure! ſuch <hi>avengements</hi> from an <hi>offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> and highly <hi>provoked</hi> God! The <hi>devouring</hi> flames that have waſted many <hi>famous</hi> Cities in former ages; <hi>viz. Conſtantinople, Rome, Alexandria</hi> in <hi>Aegypt, Paris, Amſterdam, Hambur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough,</hi> the late <hi>Imperial</hi> City of <hi>Aka</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> yea, and in this our <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> too, (as wee finde upon record in <hi>antient</hi> ſtory, and as well in the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Dutch,</hi> as our own <hi>Engliſh</hi> Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles,) came ſhort of this.</p>
            <p>Nor indeed were the <hi>ſins</hi> of any of them all, of ſo <hi>deep</hi> a Dye,
<pb facs="tcp:152194:4"/>and aggravated with <hi>ſuch incenſing</hi> circumſtances, as the <hi>ſins</hi> of <hi>this our England,</hi> and eſpecially of <hi>London,</hi> are, ſome of the <hi>chief</hi> of which, the <hi>iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of the times is come to that <hi>heighth,</hi> as not to <hi>ſuffer</hi> them to be ſo much as <hi>mentioned;</hi> and if they muſt not be ſo much as <hi>mentioned,</hi> how can they bee <hi>confeſſed?</hi> and <hi>when</hi> will they be <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken?</hi> Oh poor <hi>ſinful England!</hi> Oh <hi>England, laden</hi> with iniquity! <hi>when wilt thou be reformed? when wilt thou be waſhed from thy filthineſs? when ſhall it once bee?</hi> doſt thou look for <hi>healing,</hi> and yet all the while doſt what thou canſt, to make thy wounds <hi>wider?</hi> and thou the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of <hi>England, once famous London,</hi> canſt <hi>thou</hi> hope for better things? upon <hi>what</hi> ground I pray? doſt thou <hi>at all</hi> repent of thy <hi>manifold</hi> tranſgreſſions, and thy <hi>migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> ſins? doſt thou <hi>at all</hi> prepare to <hi>meet the Lord in the way of his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</hi> were <hi>this</hi> evident, there would be <hi>ſome hope</hi> indeed: <hi>Then</hi> perhaps,
<pb facs="tcp:152194:5"/>thoſe <hi>good words, and comfortable words,</hi> which the Angel ſpake to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Zachary</hi> (chap. 1.13, 16.) <hi>viz.</hi> that he would <hi>return to Jeruſalem with mercies,</hi> after it had been <hi>burnt</hi> 70 years before, by the <hi>Chaldean</hi> Army, may bee <hi>applicable</hi> to <hi>thee</hi> alſo. But alas! is there any, the leaſt <hi>appearance</hi> of ſuch a ſpirit as <hi>this</hi> among us? ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nothing leſs: For <hi>who,</hi> or <hi>where</hi> (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt) are <hi>any</hi> to be found, that do <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed</hi> lay things to heart? <hi>where</hi> are the <hi>men</hi> and <hi>women,</hi> that <hi>mourn, that ſigh, for the abominations of the Land?</hi> for the <hi>deteſtable things of the Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry?</hi> Such as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> complained of in his time, chap. 5.11. and chap. 8. throughout; <hi>where</hi> are <hi>any</hi> that <hi>lay to heart</hi> the <hi>afflictions</hi> of <hi>Joſeph?</hi> nay, that are affected with their <hi>own</hi> afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in any ſuch <hi>meaſure</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> as they ought? is not the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of things already <hi>off?</hi> nay, rather was it <hi>ever</hi> on, ſo as it <hi>ought</hi> to have been? for how elſe could it bee <hi>ſo ſoon</hi> gone
<pb facs="tcp:152194:5"/>again? do we not ſee men walk every day through the <hi>heaps of rubbiſh with dry Eyes?</hi> yea, with <hi>merry</hi> Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances? as if <hi>London</hi> were <hi>London</hi> ſtill, and had known <hi>no</hi> ſorrow, or <hi>felt the force</hi> of ſuch a conſuming Fire? and (which of all things elſe to me, is as <hi>calamitous,</hi> as any that can be named, and as <hi>bad</hi> an <hi>Omen</hi>) are not <hi>many, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many,</hi> even of thoſe that <hi>ſuffered moſt</hi> in their <hi>Trades, loſſes,</hi> and ſad ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of both, as <hi>little affected</hi> as any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and as <hi>unreformed? Mercies</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore did <hi>no good</hi> upon them, neither <hi>ſparing</hi> mercies, whilſt ſaved from that <hi>over-ſpreading Plague,</hi> that carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſo many of their <hi>Neighbours, Friends, Kindred,</hi> and <hi>Relations;</hi> nor <hi>inriching</hi> mercies, by which they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded in the things of this life; and now <hi>Judgements do no good</hi> upon them neither, no, though thereby reduced to <hi>great</hi> extremities, and become the <hi>objects of miſery</hi> to all that know them. Oh! how muſt this <hi>inſenſibility,</hi> this
<pb facs="tcp:152194:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>incorrigibleneſs,</hi> needs <hi>exaſperate</hi> an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God? if people will not return to him when he <hi>contends</hi> with them, when he <hi>ſmites,</hi> and ſmites ſo <hi>ſmartly</hi> too, and ſeems to threaten yet <hi>worſe</hi> things, <hi>when</hi> will they return? Truly the <hi>ſight</hi> of this, were there <hi>nothing elſe</hi> to trouble one, would make a <hi>true mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> in <hi>Zion,</hi> not care how <hi>ſoon</hi> he were taken out of this <hi>evil</hi> World, no more to <hi>have to do</hi> with it. Farewel therefore, Courteous Reader, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou art, and let <hi>you</hi> and <hi>I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare</hi> with all ſpeed for heaven. This is the <hi>counſel,</hi> and ſhall bee (through Grace) the <hi>practice</hi> of him, that as <hi>paſsionately</hi> wiſheth for <hi>thine</hi> eternal welfare, as for his <hi>own.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:152194:6"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Section. 1.</hi> THe Words explained, the Text divided, and Doctrines raiſed.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Section. 2.</hi> The firſt Doctrine propounded, and the method laid down, for the handling of it.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Section. 3.</hi> The true cauſes aſsigned, that juſtly fill men with horrour and dread, at the thoughts of death, and ſo render them much affraid, and unwilling to dye.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Section. 4.</hi> What it is that gives a good and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient relief againſt the fear of death, greatly fortifying and encouraging the heart; when it makes its approach unto it. Where firſt, the remedy is laid down generally.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Section. 5.</hi> Two more ſpecial remedies added to the former, <hi>viz.</hi> A reconciled God, and a good conſcience. Where firſt, of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled God.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Section. 6.</hi> Of a good Conſcience, which is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb facs="tcp:152194:7"/>ſpecial remedy; and wherein it conſiſts, there are two branches. It is a quiet Conſcience, and an excuſing Conſcience; A quiet Conſcience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts alſo in two things. <hi>(1)</hi> In a ſettled and well grounded peace. <hi>(2)</hi> In being void of offence, both towards God, and towards men. Where of the firſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Section. 7.</hi> Of the ſecond branch of a quiet Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; namely a conſcience void of offence, both towards God, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Section. 8.</hi> Of an excuſing Conſcience, which makes its own defence. <hi>(1)</hi> Againſt the challenge of exacting juſtice. <hi>(2)</hi> Againſt the malice of an accuſing De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Section. 9.</hi> Two important Objections anſwered, againſt the preceding Doctrine, and what hath been ſaid upon it.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Section. 10.</hi> The Uſes and improvement of the point. Firſt by way of Information, and then of Exhortation both to good and bad.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152194:7"/>
            <head>SICK-BED Thoughts;</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PHIL. 1.23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Having a deſire to depart, and to be with Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 1.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The words explained, the Text divided, and Doctrines raiſed.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>AMong the <hi>many advantages</hi> that accrued to the <hi>Goſpel</hi> in general, and to <hi>Pauls own</hi> ſpirit, in particular, from his <hi>ſufferings</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> this was <hi>one;</hi> that he was gotten <hi>looſe</hi> from the world, was <hi>raiſed</hi> in his deſires after <hi>heaven,</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:152194:8"/>and in more <hi>vehement</hi> longings after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo the words (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>having a deſire,</hi> plainly intimate, The words are very <hi>emphatical,</hi> and ſaies <hi>Zanchy</hi> upon the place, import three things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. An <hi>ardency</hi> of affection, from <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ardere,</hi> which ſignifies to burn; whence, <hi>appetitus ardens, effrenis libido,</hi> a <hi>burning</hi> deſire, a <hi>ſtrong, vigorous,</hi> and <hi>intenſe</hi> deſire; with great <hi>vehemency</hi> and <hi>earneſtneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. This deſire is <hi>intrinſecal,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductive by the ſoul <hi>only</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) 'tis <hi>properly</hi> the work of the <hi>minde,</hi> which is the <hi>fountain</hi> from whence all deſires flow, the <hi>mint</hi> where they are all coyned; as that is, <hi>ſuch</hi> are the deſires, <hi>good</hi> or <hi>bad:</hi> If that be <hi>holy, pure, active, heavenly,</hi> ſo are the deſires; but if the minde and heart be <hi>impure, cool,</hi> and <hi>faint</hi> in its affections towards God, and the <hi>things</hi> of God, then the <hi>deſires are ſo too,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure, weak, and faint; therefore</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:152194:8"/> 3. The participle of the <hi>preſent</hi> tenſe (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>having</hi> a deſire, notes a <hi>continued</hi> act, a deſire <hi>alwaies</hi> in acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ever working, till the <hi>thing</hi> deſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed bee <hi>accompliſhed,</hi> and <hi>fully</hi> attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: It is not <hi>ſlothful,</hi> nor <hi>idle</hi> at all, puts a man upon running without <hi>wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs,</hi> upon praying without <hi>ceaſing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this deſire here, is carried out after <hi>two</hi> things; to <hi>depart,</hi> and to <hi>go to Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, To <hi>depart</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) or, to be <hi>diſſolved,</hi> ſay our old Engliſh Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, agreeable to <hi>Jerome</hi>'s Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by the <hi>Latin</hi> word <hi>diſſolvi,</hi> which is to bee <hi>reſolved</hi> into our <hi>firſt</hi> princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, the body to the <hi>duſt,</hi> and the <hi>ſpirit</hi> to God that gave it: Which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>Scaliger</hi> and <hi>Eraſmus</hi> follow. Many <hi>learned</hi> men have <hi>criticiſed</hi> upon <hi>this</hi> Greek word, and given their <hi>various</hi> opinions about the <hi>true</hi> notion of it; the <hi>chief</hi> of which, becauſe they have ſomething of <hi>inſtruction</hi> in them, I will here take notice of, and recollect toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:152194:9"/>
               <p> Sometimes 'tis the <hi>Marriners</hi> word, (<hi>verbum a nautis tranſlatum,</hi> ſaies <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſmus</hi>) when he doth <hi>(ſoluere An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choram)</hi> looſen his Ship, <hi>weigh</hi> Anchor, and upon the very <hi>firſt</hi> fair wind, makes <hi>haſte</hi> to bee gone to his <hi>deſired</hi> Port: Thus the <hi>Syriack</hi> reads it; ſo doth <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> and ſome others. And indeed, what is <hi>this life</hi> of ours here in <hi>this</hi> World, but a <hi>flit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> up and down, and <hi>changing</hi> place, as a <hi>Ship</hi> at Sea, that <hi>ſtill is paſsing</hi> to and fro, from <hi>ſhore</hi> to <hi>ſhore?</hi> and whilſt it doth ſo, doth it not meet with <hi>many troubleſome</hi> and <hi>rough</hi> Seas? and is it not <hi>often</hi> endangered by <hi>high</hi> winds, <hi>boiſterous</hi> waves, <hi>rocks</hi> and <hi>quickſands?</hi> than which, what can be a more <hi>lively Emblem</hi> of the life of man, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies encounters <hi>ſo many hazards</hi> and <hi>toſsings,</hi> till at laſt it grows <hi>leaky</hi> and <hi>crazy,</hi> like an <hi>over-worn</hi> Ship, that can <hi>ſail</hi> no longer? and is it any mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, if then it be willing to <hi>weigh An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor,</hi> and get with what <hi>ſpeed</hi> it may,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152194:9"/>to the <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Haven</hi> of its <hi>reſt?</hi> Even an <hi>Heathen</hi> hath paſſed <hi>this ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence</hi> upon the life of man, <hi>Seneca</hi> by name, who, writing to <hi>Polybius,</hi> hath theſe words, (<hi>in hoc tam procelloſo &amp; in omnes tempeſtates expoſito mari, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vigantibus, nullus portus niſi mortis eſt.</hi> Ad Polyb. c. 28.) in this <hi>tumultuous</hi> and <hi>ſtormy</hi> ſea, expoſed to all <hi>manner</hi> of tempeſts, no <hi>ſafe</hi> Port is found to the Saylers, but that of <hi>Death.</hi> The like paſſage <hi>Ambroſe</hi> hath after him in his Book, <hi>de bono mortis, c.</hi> 8. <hi>Juſto mors ſalutis portus,</hi> to a juſt man, death on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is the ſafeſt Haven.</p>
               <p>Sometimes 'tis the <hi>Souldiers</hi> word, when hee doth <hi>(ſoluere funes)</hi> at the command of his General, <hi>looſen his Tent</hi> in which hee lies upon the ground, <hi>plucks</hi> up the ſtakes, <hi>unties</hi> the cords, that he may <hi>quit</hi> his old quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for <hi>new</hi> ones: And what <hi>metaphor</hi> can bee <hi>more proper</hi> than this alſo, to ſet forth our <hi>condition</hi> here? for is not the life of <hi>every good</hi> Chriſtian in this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152194:10"/>World, a <hi>Souldiers life,</hi> under his <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain General?</hi> and muſt he not alwaies be, both in a <hi>fighting</hi> and <hi>moving</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, ready to <hi>follow</hi> his <hi>General</hi> where-ever he marcheth? muſt he not <hi>ſit looſe</hi> from every place, and carry, as I may ſo ſay, his <hi>Tent</hi> with him, to <hi>pitch</hi> it down, and <hi>take it up</hi> again, as occaſion ſerves; till at laſt the <hi>cords</hi> be not only <hi>looſned,</hi> but <hi>broken,</hi> and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially that <hi>ſilver-cord,</hi> mentioned in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.6. by which the ſoul is <hi>faſtened</hi> to its body, as to its <hi>Tent?</hi> and what elſe do the two great Apoſtles, <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul,</hi> mean, but <hi>this,</hi> when they ſpeak of their <hi>earthly Tabernacles,</hi> in which <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, he <hi>groaned</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2, 4.) and which <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid, he <hi>muſt ſhortly put off</hi> (2 Pet. 1.14.) <hi>Eraſmus</hi> falls in with <hi>this</hi> conſtruction of the Word likewiſe, as well as of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
               <p>Sometimes 'tis the <hi>Waggoners,</hi> or <hi>Carriers</hi> Word (<hi>verbum ab aurig is ductum,</hi> ſaies <hi>Beza</hi>) when he doth <hi>(ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152194:10"/>lora)</hi> unharneſs his Horſes at his journey's end. And do we not <hi>unhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> as 'twere, and put <hi>all off</hi> when we <hi>prepare</hi> for the grave, towards which wee have been fetching <hi>many</hi> a <hi>weary</hi> ſtep, and drawing many a <hi>hard</hi> draught all our life-time, and this too, with many a <hi>ſmart</hi> laſh, and ſometimes <hi>goades,</hi> to <hi>quicken</hi> us, how <hi>gawled</hi> ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our <hi>ſides</hi> have been, in the mean while, with <hi>heart-akeing</hi> cares and griefs, and the ſorrows which we <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very</hi> day meet with.</p>
               <p>Sometimes 'tis the <hi>priſoner's</hi> word, when he doth, <hi>ſolvere vincula &amp; cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas poſt ſe relinquere,</hi> unfetter and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhackle himſelf, or hath his <hi>bonds</hi> and his <hi>chains</hi> knocked off, as <hi>Peter's</hi> were by the <hi>Angel</hi> when he was in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, (<hi>Acts</hi> 12.7.) And this is the way <hi>Tremelius</hi> ſeems to go while he tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late's the word <hi>(Liberari)</hi> to be ſet at <hi>liberty,</hi> or <hi>freed</hi> out of priſon. <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras</hi> that knew nothing <hi>above,</hi> or <hi>beſides</hi> nature, could inſtruct <hi>his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:152194:11"/>in this, that the Body is but a <hi>priſon</hi> to the Soul; and that it is one of the <hi>chiefeſt</hi> buſineſſes of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, <hi>(animam de carcere corporis libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare)</hi> to deliver the ſoul from the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the body, as he is quoted by <hi>Jerome</hi> againſt <hi>Ruffinus:</hi> And many times what a <hi>dark, loathſome,</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable</hi> priſon is it? a kind of a <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty</hi> and <hi>filthy</hi> dungeon, eſpecially to men of <hi>melancholly</hi> conſtitutions, and under the power of their own <hi>filthy lusts,</hi> and <hi>guilty-conſciences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sometimes ſayes <hi>Eraſmus</hi> again, It imports as much as <hi>(farcinas colligere, &amp; ad iter preparare)</hi> to take up ones pack and be gone, and ſo it is a word proper to <hi>Porters</hi> and <hi>Pedlars,</hi> which carry heavy <hi>burdens,</hi> and <hi>packs</hi> at their back, as having no other Trade to drive but this. And I pray, what is <hi>this body</hi> of ours, but a <hi>burden</hi> of clay, a <hi>clog</hi> of freſh, which we every day, where-ever we go, do bear about with us? And oh <hi>how heavy</hi> and <hi>tire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:152194:11"/>is it in a time of <hi>ſickneſs</hi> to be troubled with it! How <hi>painful</hi> to the <hi>weary</hi> bones, and the <hi>feeble</hi> knees, to <hi>tumble</hi> and <hi>toſs,</hi> firſt on the ſide and then on the other, and this an <hi>hundred</hi> times in a night! Sometimes <hi>chill</hi> and cold, cauſing every joint to <hi>ſhake,</hi> and as it were to beat together; at other times, all in <hi>flames</hi> and <hi>burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> like a <hi>fiery</hi> Oven! After which, perhaps, 'tis <hi>parboyl'd</hi> in its own moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, and at laſt, left ſo <hi>faint</hi> and <hi>weak,</hi> as if all its <hi>nimble</hi> and <hi>volatile</hi> ſpirits had quite forſaken it! Hath not many a <hi>ſtrong</hi> man, many a <hi>luſty, hail, debonair</hi> ſon of <hi>Adam</hi> been thus <hi>ſurprized</hi> on a ſudden? Once it was my lot to be in company (on a <hi>Tueſday-night</hi>) with a perſon of as <hi>great</hi> ſtrength and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour, as any I knew: who ſpeaking of his great <hi>proweſſe</hi> and <hi>courage</hi> in many feats of Activity, and particularly of his <hi>wraſtling, leaping, vaulting,</hi> and how many <hi>hundred</hi> pound weight he could take up with his <hi>Teeth,</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152194:12"/>ſwing over his head with <hi>one hand,</hi> and that with eaſe, ſtripping up his <hi>brawny</hi> arme, in a kind of a <hi>boaſting</hi> way, cauſed me to take ſome more than ordinary notice of him: but this vain man, having at that time gotten a <hi>little cold,</hi> before forty eight hours more were paſſed, was ſo <hi>enfeebled</hi> with a Rheum and Cough, that he lay <hi>groaning</hi> in a very <hi>pittiful</hi> manner, to the <hi>admiration</hi> of all that knew him, not having ſtrength enough to <hi>turn</hi> him in his bed, ſo that he dyed on the <hi>Thurſday,</hi> and the next day after, which was <hi>Friday,</hi> in the ſame week, I followed him <hi>to his grave.</hi> Well therefore doth the Prophet ſay, Let not the <hi>mighty</hi> man <hi>glory</hi> in his <hi>might;</hi> for even ſuch an one may dy in his <hi>full</hi> ſtrength: whilſt <hi>his breaſts are full of milk, and his bones are moiſtened with marrow</hi> (Job 21.23, 24.) <hi>though he be wholly at eaſe, at preſent:</hi> yet before another day comes, he may be in <hi>great pain,</hi> and upon his ſick-bed, may have
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152194:12"/>cauſe to <hi>cry out</hi> with the Apoſtle, (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4.) <hi>We groan being burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> And here, methink's, may very aptly be ſub-joined that excellent paſſage of <hi>Seneca,</hi> in the 35th. Epiſt. of his firſt Book of Epiſtles, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration whereof (referring to what went before) will elevate and lift up the Soul, ſayes he, <hi>Animum, qui gravi ſarcina preſsus, explicari cupit, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verti ad illa quorum fuit, nam corpus hoc animi pondus ac poena eſt; premente illo urgetur, in vinculis eſt, niſi accesſit Philoſophia, quae à terrenis dimittit ad divina:</hi> the Soul, which, being preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed down with an heavy burden, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to return from whence it came; for this Body of ours is but a weight and puniſhment unto the Soul, ſo long as that oppreſſeth it, 'tis as 'twere in chaines, till it returns from this earth to Heaven.</p>
               <p>Sometimes 'tis the <hi>Traveller's</hi> word, when he doth <hi>(migrare ex hoſpitio)</hi> quit his Inne, and goes far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152194:13"/>on, and ſo <hi>Beza</hi> tranſlates it, as ſome others before him had done: and what <hi>thence</hi> can we infer, but that this world is no more than an <hi>Inne?</hi> where we make but a <hi>little ſtay,</hi> having a <hi>jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> to go, and ſo muſt not take up our abode here. Excellently ſpeaks <hi>M. T. Cicero,</hi> in his <hi>Cato major. Ex vita hac diſcedo, tanquam ex hoſpitio, non tanquam ex domo, commorandi enim natura, diverſorium nobis, non habitandi, dedit:</hi> I depart out of this life, as out of an Inne, not as out of an Houſe, Nature having given it to us, as a place only to lodge in for a ſhort time, not to dwell in.</p>
               <p>Sometimes 'tis the <hi>Strangers</hi> word, who is a kind of <hi>Pilgrim</hi> abroad in <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign</hi> Countryes, far from home, which when he deſires, and is reſolved to repair to, either as <hi>weary</hi> of his <hi>wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings,</hi> or by a <hi>call</hi> from his Father who ſent him thither, is then ſaid (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>redire Domum</hi>) to return home: Thus <hi>Athanaſius</hi> takes it; yea, and a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152194:13"/>greater than he, even the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> it ſelf, (<hi>Luke</hi> 12.36.) where, when the <hi>great Lord</hi> there mentioned, is ſaid to <hi>return home,</hi> 'tis thus phraſed, (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) Now how <hi>aptly</hi> this alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth our condition here, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures do frequently tell us. For did not the <hi>Patriarchs</hi> of old ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count themſelves as <hi>pilgrims</hi> and <hi>ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> in this world? What ſayes <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> (Gen. 47.9.) <hi>The dayes of the yeares of my pilgrimage are an hundred and thirty yeares, few and evil have the dayes of the yeares of my life been, and have not attained to the dayes of the yeares of the life of my Fathers, in the dayes of their pilgrimage.</hi> So <hi>David,</hi> (Pſalm 39.12.) <hi>I am a ſtranger with thee, and a ſojourner, as all my fathers were:</hi> And hath it not been <hi>thus</hi> with all the ſons of men, <hi>in all ages?</hi> though 'tis true, <hi>few,</hi> or none almoſt but <hi>good</hi> men have thought ſo, that have been <hi>thorowly</hi> convinced, and believed that their <hi>home</hi> is ſomewhere elſe, even <hi>in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152194:14"/>heaven</hi> where their <hi>father</hi> dwells: there, there it is, that they have a <hi>dwelling indeed,</hi> a dwelling properly their <hi>own,</hi> an houſe built on <hi>purpoſe</hi> for them, a <hi>ſure</hi> houſe that will alwayes be <hi>new,</hi> and never grow old, that is <hi>their home,</hi> and thither they <hi>all</hi> haſten, even upon the very firſt call of their <hi>heavenly</hi> Father.</p>
               <p>Once more ere I leave this Word, and then Ile have done with it. <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> about the middle of his Book <hi>de Patientia,</hi> tranſlates it thus, <hi>Cupio recipi jam,</hi> I deſire now to be <hi>received,</hi> or <hi>taken up,</hi> (he means into the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens): as 'tis ſaid of <hi>Christ himſelf,</hi> when he aſcended (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>he was received up into heaven,</hi> (Mark 16.19.) <hi>Luke</hi> varies the word, and ſayes, (Chap. 24.50. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>he was carried up.</hi> And (in <hi>Acts</hi> 1.9. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>he was caught up, and a Cloud received him;</hi> it comes all to one, and intimates thus much, that in our <hi>paſſage</hi> out of this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152194:14"/>life to Heaven, we are not <hi>alone,</hi> but are accompanied with <hi>bleſſed Angels,</hi> that do as 'twere <hi>wait</hi> to receive our ſoules, as ſoon as ever they <hi>leave our bodies,</hi> and then <hi>carry</hi> them up, where they carried the ſoul of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> even <hi>into Abrahams boſome,</hi> (Luke 16.22.) and this was it which the Apoſtle <hi>lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged</hi> for, and which it ſeems, as to his <hi>own particular</hi> he moſt deſired, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to be <hi>carried up to heaven,</hi> as I may ſo ſay, on the <hi>wings of Angels:</hi> he had often fled thither himſelf upon the wings of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> but now he would fain go thither for <hi>good and all,</hi> as our Proverb is; he would have the <hi>winged Cherubims</hi> now come and <hi>fetch</hi> him from hence, as being <hi>weary</hi> of ſtaying here any longer; I, but <hi>whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> would he be fetched? <hi>whether</hi> would he go? Himſelf tells us, He <hi>would go to Chriſt,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>I deſire to depart, and to be with Chriſt;</hi> Mark the words, he doth not ſay, I deſire to <hi>go to heaven,</hi> or to be among
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152194:15"/>the ſoules of <hi>juſt men made perfect;</hi> to be where the <hi>general Aſſembly of the firſt-born</hi> are; or to be in the <hi>heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Jeruſalem,</hi> to be a <hi>glorified Saint,</hi> and among the <hi>innumerable company of Angles,</hi> but, <hi>to be with Christ,</hi> as if that were <hi>(inſtar-omnium)</hi> in ſtead of all, or better than all. Heaven it ſelf is not <hi>ſo much an Heaven</hi> to an holy heart, no, not when it is in Heaven, <hi>as Chriſt is;</hi> all the reſt of the glories there, <hi>are but beams of this Sun:</hi> it is the preſence of <hi>Chriſt only,</hi> and of <hi>God in Chriſt,</hi> that makes Heaven, Heaven: <hi>(Coelum ipſum non eſſet Coelum, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente Chriſto)</hi> Heaven it ſelf would be no Heaven, if Chriſt were abſent.</p>
               <p>But perhaps ſome will ſay, Was Chriſt <hi>abſent</hi> from <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Paul</hi> from him, and that <hi>even now</hi> at this time, when he ſayes, he deſires <hi>to be with him?</hi> How could he have been ſo <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant,</hi> ſo <hi>couragious,</hi> ſo <hi>bold</hi> for the truth, and that even in the face of the <hi>Imperial Court</hi> it ſelf, under the very
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152194:15"/>
                  <hi>noſe</hi> of that <hi>bloody Nero,</hi> that was then Reſident at <hi>Rome,</hi> while he was a <hi>priſoner</hi> there, had not Chriſt been with him? and been with him, <hi>i more than an ordinary</hi> manner?</p>
               <p>To which I muſt anſwer without any denyal at all, that it is moſt true; a <hi>great preſence</hi> of Chriſt was with him, no doubt is to be made of it: how elſe could he have <hi>ſuffered ſo great things</hi> for his Name, as was by Chriſt himſelf foretold he ſhould, (<hi>Acts</hi> 9.16.)? How elſe could he have run through <hi>ſo many</hi> and <hi>great</hi> ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, which himſelf innumerates in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.23-29. Where he tells us, that he was <hi>in labours more abundant, than any other of the Miniſters of Chriſt, in ſtripes above meaſure; in priſons more frequently, in deaths oft: Of the Jews five times received I forty ſtripes ſave one: thrice was I beaten with Reds: once was I ſtoned: thrice I ſuffered ſhip-wrack: a night and a day I have been in the deep: In Journeys often: in perils of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152194:16"/>waters: in perils of Robbers: in perils by mine own Countrey-men: in perils by the Heathen: in perils in the City: in perils in the Wilderneſſe: in perils in the Sea: in perils among falſe Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: in wearineſs and painfulneſs: in watchings often: in hunger and thirſt, in fastings often: in cold and nakedneſſe, beſides thoſe things that are without</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>that which cometh upon me daily, the care of all the Churches.</hi> Now had not Chriſt been with him in <hi>all</hi> theſe troubles, what had <hi>become</hi> of him? would not the <hi>wrath</hi> of men have <hi>ſwallowed</hi> him up? The manifold <hi>dangers</hi> he encountred with, have <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed</hi> him? Would not both Sea and Land have been <hi>againſt</hi> him, and many a time have <hi>devoured</hi> him? Yes verily, had it not been that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was with him, <hi>ſtrengthening</hi> him, <hi>ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> him, <hi>comforting</hi> him, <hi>enabling</hi> him both to <hi>do,</hi> and <hi>endure</hi> all things, he had been as miſerable a man as had
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152194:16"/>been then alive. But it is moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that <hi>Chriſt was indeed with him,</hi> and took as much care of him, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>good maſter</hi> did of a moſt <hi>faithful ſervant,</hi> or the moſt <hi>benigne Prince</hi> did of a moſt <hi>loyal Subject,</hi> that did him the moſt ſingular and eminent ſervice.</p>
               <p>But though this be acknowledged, and cannot be in the leaſt denyed, yet <hi>Pauls</hi> words are not <hi>vain</hi> words, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way <hi>inconſiſtent</hi> with this Truth: when he ſaith, <hi>He deſires to depart, and to be with Chriſt:</hi> For,</p>
               <p>Firſt, Though <hi>Chriſt</hi> was <hi>with</hi> him in, and by his <hi>Spirit;</hi> with him in his <hi>Image</hi> upon his Soul, and the <hi>divine impreſsions</hi> thereof upon his Heart: Though he was with him by <hi>protecting</hi> him, <hi>bleſſing</hi> him, <hi>delivering</hi> him from a <hi>thouſand</hi> evils, that otherwiſe would have befallen him. Though he had many a <hi>kind meſſage</hi> from Chriſt, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a <hi>ſweet Love-letter,</hi> as I may ſo ſpeak: yea, and more than all this,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152194:17"/>many a precious <hi>Jewel,</hi> as 'twere ſent as Tokens from him; though he found and felt the ſecret <hi>influences of Chriſt</hi> ſhed all abroad in him, and ſuch pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful <hi>attractions</hi> after him, by the effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of his <hi>Oyntments</hi> and <hi>ſweet ſmel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Myrrhs;</hi> yet all theſe were ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>things</hi> of Chriſt, and ſome expreſſions of good will from him at a <hi>diſtance,</hi> than <hi>Chriſt himſelf.</hi> It was the <hi>Perſon</hi> of Chriſt that he deſired: I mean, his <hi>perſonal preſence,</hi> and <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal communion</hi> with him: not onely <hi>intereſt</hi> in him, (for this he had where ere he was) <hi>but Viſion,</hi> as <hi>Penelope</hi> ſaid to her <hi>Ulyſſes. Ovid.</hi> Ep. 1.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nil mihi reſcribas, attamen ipſe veni.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Twill not ſuffice if thou thy Letters ſend,</l>
                  <l>Thy preſence only will the matter mend.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Write what he would: 'twas <hi>himſelf</hi> onely coming in <hi>perſon</hi> to her that would ſatisfie her. Thus the <hi>Perſian Lady</hi> to her Prince, when he offered her a very precious <hi>Jewel</hi> to wear
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152194:17"/>for his ſake, 'tis <hi>your ſelf</hi> Sir I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to enjoy <hi>(Tu mihi, ſola gemma es)</hi> theſe <hi>without you</hi> loſe their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, and in my account will be little worth. In like manner our <hi>Apoſtle</hi> here, placeth his <hi>chiefeſt</hi> happineſſe in the <hi>ſight</hi> of Chriſt, and <hi>being in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> with him. <hi>Bernard</hi> (in <hi>Pſal. qui Habit.</hi>) expreſſeth it to the life: <hi>Eſſe Chriſtum cum Paulo magna ſecuritas: eſſe Paulum cum Chriſto ſumma foelici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,</hi> Chriſt his being with <hi>Paul</hi> was his great ſecurity; but <hi>Paul's</hi> being with Chriſt, was his higheſt felicity.</p>
               <p>Secondly, when <hi>Paul</hi> deſires to be with Chriſt, the meaning of it in <hi>this</hi> place is, <hi>ſo to be with him,</hi> as to have the moſt <hi>full enjoyment</hi> of him that he could be made capable of, to be in the <hi>full view</hi> of him, even <hi>face to face;</hi> Here he had but <hi>glympſes</hi> of him, and that <hi>by faith onely,</hi> and through <hi>thick clonds,</hi> and this but <hi>now and then</hi> too, which though <hi>very refreſhing</hi> to him, yet <hi>far</hi> from making up <hi>ſuch</hi> a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152194:18"/>as the <hi>conſtant</hi> and <hi>un-inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted</hi> enjoyment of him would give. <hi>This,</hi> and nothing <hi>leſs</hi> than this will put an end to his deſires, and afford him the <hi>content</hi> he ſeeks for, <hi>omnis motus tendit in quietem,</hi> all motion aims at reſt, but <hi>this</hi> moſt of all.</p>
               <p>Thus we have the Apoſtles <hi>deſires,</hi> what they are, and how vehement, and the object about which they are converſant, together with the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium, or way for the attaining of them: <hi>he would depart and be with Chriſt,</hi> Let us next ſee the reaſon of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>which is far better,</hi> ſo 'tis tranſlated: but it would be <hi>better</hi> expreſſed by a right Engliſhing of the <hi>cauſative particle</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>for: for</hi> it is far better, <hi>far better, multo magis melius,</hi> ſaies the vulgar tranſlation, much more better: <hi>Longè enim optimum eſt,</hi> ſaies <hi>Beza,</hi> for that is farre the beſt. Properly, the words may be rendred, by <hi>much rather bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, better by much;</hi> or, as 'tis in the old
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152194:18"/>bibles, <hi>beſt of all.</hi> But for whom? not for <hi>you,</hi> ſaies the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> but for <hi>me,</hi> I am ſure. Indeed for <hi>your ſakes;</hi> Methinks I could be content <hi>to ſtay a while longer;</hi> but when I conſider how <hi>ſweet</hi> it will be, <hi>to be with Chriſt</hi> for <hi>altogether,</hi> and in the <hi>higheſt</hi> and <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt</hi> enjoyment of him, then I am <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient till I am with him.</hi> His love to the <hi>Phillippians</hi> was <hi>great,</hi> and his love to <hi>himſelf</hi> was <hi>great too;</hi> Willing he was for <hi>their</hi> ſakes to ſtay, and yet for his <hi>own</hi> ſake <hi>more willing</hi> to go. <hi>Ego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met mihi proximus ipſi,</hi> I am neareſt to my ſelf, may every man ſay. It were ſomething <hi>ſtrange,</hi> if a man ſhould not love himſelf <hi>first,</hi> I was about to ſay <hi>beſt</hi> too, next unto the <hi>God</hi> that <hi>made him,</hi> and <hi>ſweet Jeſus</hi> his <hi>Redeemer;</hi> yet <hi>Paul</hi> ſayes, that even in <hi>this</hi> caſe he was in a <hi>ſtraight</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>I am in a ſtraight between two:</hi> he was <hi>beſieged</hi> on both ſides, which to yield to he doth not <hi>well</hi> know, but at laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves, that <hi>for their furtherance and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152194:19"/>joy of faith,</hi> if Chriſt ſhould ſee fit <hi>he would abide and continue</hi> yet longer with them; <hi>verſ.</hi> 24.25. he that could wiſh himſelf even <hi>accuſed</hi> from Chriſt <hi>(amazing expreſſion!) for his brethren his kinſmen according to the fleſh</hi> (<hi>Rom.</hi> 9.3.) was here willing, all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, to come ſomewhat the <hi>later</hi> to Heaven, (which yet he <hi>moſt</hi> of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired) <hi>on condition</hi> to <hi>help on</hi> the word of the Goſpel yet <hi>a little further,</hi> and to give a more <hi>firm eſtabliſhment</hi> to the Churches of Chriſt. <hi>Oh rare tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per!</hi> What an holy <hi>struggle</hi> was now in <hi>Pauls</hi> heart, between the love which he bare to <hi>Chriſt and his people</hi> in this World, and the love which he bare to <hi>Chriſt and himſelf</hi> in the other World! Will it not be <hi>hard</hi> to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, in which of theſe he exerciſed the <hi>greateſt</hi> Grace? and alſo <hi>which</hi> of the <hi>two</hi> graces now at work in his heart was the <hi>moſt noble:</hi> his <hi>ſelf-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyal,</hi> or his <hi>ſelf-love?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But enough of gloſſing upon the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152194:19"/>Words, which I have been the larger in, in reference to what will follow in the ſeveral Points to be handled from them.</p>
               <p>As for the diviſion of them, they fall into <hi>two</hi> parts: (1) a <hi>declaration</hi> of the Apoſtles deſire, which is <hi>to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part and to be with Chriſt.</hi> (2) the reaſon of this his deſire, <hi>which is far better.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Doctrines ariſing from the words are <hi>theſe four:</hi> the firſt is a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine that lies <hi>couchant</hi> in them, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily <hi>implyed,</hi> though not ſo plainly <hi>expreſſed,</hi> it is this:</p>
               <p>That <hi>whoever hath a true and ſaving intereſt in Christ, hath good and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ground not to be affraid, or unwilling to dye;</hi> this I take it is included and muſt be underſtood, for he that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to dye, and to go to Chriſt, muſt needs be ſuppoſed <hi>not to be affraid, or unwilling to dye, (omne majus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines minus)</hi> every greater contains the leſſe: a man muſt firſt be <hi>paſt the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152194:20"/>fear</hi> of Death, before he can have <hi>a deſire of death,</hi> eſpecially ſuch a <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement</hi> deſire, as is here meant; as in goodneſſe. No man can be <hi>poſitively</hi> good, but he that is <hi>firſt</hi> good <hi>nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively;</hi> firſt he muſt <hi>(removere prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bens)</hi> take away that which <hi>hinders</hi> his being good, before he can be <hi>truly</hi> good; even <hi>ſo</hi> here in the caſe of death; The <hi>fear</hi> of death muſt firſt be <hi>remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> and <hi>conquered,</hi> before there can be any <hi>actual deſire,</hi> at leaſt any <hi>great</hi> and <hi>ſtrong</hi> deſire of it: This then is the firſt Doctrine.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is this: That <hi>no perſon whatſoever is ſo fit to dye, as he that can truly ſay with our Apoſtle here, he hath a deſire, an earneſt and ardent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to depart, and to be with Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third is this. <hi>A righteous man's death, is no other than a going to Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fourth this, from the ſe words, <hi>for it is much better:</hi> That <hi>there is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, very great reaſon, how happy ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a mans condition may ſeem to be in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152194:20"/>this world, yet even then when it is thus with him, to depart hence and to go to Christ; yea, and to deſire it, and that greatly.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 2.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The firſt Doctrine propounded, and the method layed down for the handling of it.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THe firſt Doctrine then is this: <hi>That whoever hath a true and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving intereſt in Christ, hath good and ſufficient ground, not to be affraid, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to dye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>method</hi> I intend to handle it in, ſhall be <hi>this:</hi> (1) To conſider what are the <hi>juſt cauſes</hi> of the fear of death. (2) What it is that gives a <hi>good and ſufficient relief</hi> againſt the ſaid fear; which, whatever it is, is likewiſe a <hi>clear evidence</hi> of a <hi>true</hi> and <hi>ſaving</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Chriſt. (3) I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to anſwer <hi>two very important</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, which may ſeem <hi>ſtrongly</hi> to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:152194:21"/>oppoſe the whole Doctrine, and all that is ſaid upon it. (4) Make uſe of the whole, partly by way of <hi>infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> and partly by way of <hi>exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and that both to good and bad.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 3.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The true cauſes aſſigned, that juſtly fill men with horrour and dread of the thoughts of death, and ſo render them much affraid, and unwilling to dye.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THere are <hi>many</hi> things that <hi>juſtly</hi> cauſe a <hi>fear</hi> of death, even a <hi>great</hi> and <hi>terrible</hi> fear.</p>
               <p>Firſt the <hi>conſciouſneſs</hi> of ſin and guilt, <hi>eſpecially</hi> in the <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regeneracy,</hi> which is alwayes accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with <hi>impenitency</hi> and <hi>unbelief;</hi> the two <hi>damning ſins,</hi> not but that all <hi>other</hi> ſins, even the <hi>leaſt</hi> that is, hath <hi>demerit</hi> and <hi>provocation</hi> enough in it, to <hi>damn</hi> any one that is guilty of it,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152194:21"/>but <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance</hi> where-ever they are in <hi>Truth,</hi> will <hi>take all off;</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>millions</hi> of guilts, and make the <hi>blackeſt ſins</hi> that are, <hi>as white as ſnow; ſcarlet and crimſon ſins to bee as wool,</hi> (Iſa. 1.18.) Now where <hi>theſe</hi> are wanting, and ſo the <hi>guilt</hi> and <hi>filth</hi> of every ſin <hi>remaining,</hi> and upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions <hi>flying</hi> in a mans face, and fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their <hi>venomous ſtings</hi> in his heart and conſcience: How <hi>terrible</hi> muſt this needs be? For do not thoughts of the <hi>wages</hi> which <hi>theſe</hi> ſins not <hi>repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> of, do <hi>deſerve,</hi> come pouring in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, as at all times, ſo <hi>most</hi> of all when <hi>Death</hi> approaches? Though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he <hi>lull'd</hi> his conſcience <hi>aſleep,</hi> and would not ſuffer it to be <hi>awakened,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by a quickning <hi>Soul-ſearching</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, nor the <hi>plain-dealing</hi> of faithful friends: Yet now <hi>Satan</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> too, will both ſpeak, and <hi>ſpeak aloud</hi> too; yea, though <hi>Satan</hi> ſhould <hi>ſay nothing,</hi> but be altogether ſilent; yet <hi>ſelf-accuſations,</hi> and <hi>ſelf-condemnations</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:152194:22"/>will ſpeak enough to fill the ſoul with <hi>horror,</hi> and leave it in <hi>ſuch diſtreſſes,</hi> as <hi>no remedy</hi> can be found, for while the aforeſaid <hi>impenitency</hi> and <hi>unbelief</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains to be (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>à ſemet ipſo damnatus</hi>) ſelf-condemned: Who can expreſs the <hi>terror</hi> of it? and indeed <hi>this</hi> is that, not ſo much <hi>Death</hi> it ſelf, as begets ſo <hi>much fear</hi> and dread: As <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his diſcourſe <hi>de bono mortis,</hi> doth learnedly argue; where in his eighth Chapter, he hath many excellent paſſages to this purpoſe: <hi>Mors peccatorum peſsima</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>non utique mors peſsima generaliter, ſed peſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſima ſpecialiter peccatorum, unde liquet acerbitatem non mortis eſſe, ſed culpae;</hi> the death of ſinners is the worſt of deaths, not death in <hi>general,</hi> but the death of <hi>ſinners;</hi> From whence 'tis evident, that the <hi>bitterneſs</hi> is not <hi>from death</hi> it ſelf, but <hi>from the crimes</hi> that merit it. Again a little farther, he hath theſe words: <hi>ſuae igitur unuſquiſque conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae vulnus accuſet, non mortis acerbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem.</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:152194:22"/>Let every one therefore that by his Sin hath wounded his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, lay the blame there, and not upon death. And again, <hi>Non enim habemus, quod in morte metuamus, ſi rihil quod timendum ſit, vita noſtra co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſit;</hi> There will be no cauſe of fear in death, if in our life-time we have done nothing, that we have cauſe to be afraid of. Once again, <hi>Prudentibus delictorum ſupplicia terrori ſunt, delicta autem non mortucrum actus ſunt, ſed viventium;</hi> To wiſe men, the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of offences is matter of fear, now theſe are the acts, not of <hi>dead</hi>-men, but of the <hi>living:</hi> This then is the firſt thing that gives <hi>juſt cauſe</hi> of the fear of death; Sins not repented of.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The apprehenſion of <hi>Divine diſpleaſure</hi> hereupon, and the <hi>Wrath</hi> of an <hi>Offended God,</hi> a Wrath <hi>unappeaſed,</hi> an <hi>infinite</hi> wrath, a wrath <hi>intellerable,</hi> and <hi>unexpreſsible;</hi> a wrath inflicted by an <hi>Omripotent Power,</hi> in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152194:23"/>compariſon of which, all the <hi>rendings, tearings, cruciatings, burnings, rack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, torturings</hi> of mens bodies here, by <hi>all</hi> the moſt <hi>exquiſitely invented tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> upon <hi>Racks, Gibbets, Wheels, Gridirons,</hi> and other <hi>engines of cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> are but a <hi>flea-biting.</hi> The <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal</hi> torments here, I mean from the ſenſe of Divine wrath, being <hi>chiefly ſeated</hi> in, and <hi>moſtly</hi> inflicted upon the <hi>minde;</hi> not but that the body too, when 'tis riſen from the Grave, ſhall have its <hi>ſhare</hi> in theſe ſufferings in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with the ſoul, even to its <hi>ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt poſsibility</hi> of bearing them.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, An <hi>obnoxiouſneſs</hi> to all this, by the <hi>fixed</hi> Law of God, which <hi>cannot be altered,</hi> and by which he ſtands <hi>accurſed,</hi> and ſubject to all the <hi>direful threatnings</hi> thereof, ſo long as he remains in <hi>this</hi> his <hi>unregenerate</hi> and <hi>impenitent</hi> ſtate. This is another thing that adds unto his fear.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, The thoughts of that moſt <hi>juſt,</hi> and <hi>great Tribunal,</hi> at which
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152194:23"/>he muſt one day ſtand, and <hi>where</hi> an <hi>account muſt</hi> be given, of every <hi>thought, word,</hi> and <hi>deed,</hi> how <hi>wicked,</hi> how <hi>vile</hi> ſoever, and howſoever <hi>circumſtanci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated;</hi> all muſt be <hi>detected</hi> then, and laid open before <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Angels:</hi> All <hi>night-ſins, ſecret-ſins, heart-ſins;</hi> The <hi>Thief,</hi> the <hi>Murderer,</hi> the <hi>Adulterer,</hi> the <hi>cloſeſt</hi> and <hi>moſt undiſcerned</hi> Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, ſhall then be <hi>known</hi> what he is, and <hi>all his iniquities</hi> ſtart up before him: The <hi>Books</hi> ſhall be opened, the Book of a mans <hi>own Conſcience,</hi> the Book of Gods <hi>omniſciency,</hi> the Books of <hi>Record</hi> in Heaven: And then ſhall the <hi>impenitent, hardened ſinner ſtand before his great God and Creator,</hi> (who will now be his Judge) as a <hi>guilty Malefactor;</hi> and as I ſaid before, <hi>ſelf-condemned.</hi> There ſhall need no <hi>far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> evidence than <hi>himſelf againſt himſelf;</hi> All his <hi>ſcoffings</hi> and <hi>ſcornings</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>things</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> of his <hi>holy Waies, Ordinances, People;</hi> all his <hi>contempts</hi> of Chriſt, and <hi>tramplings</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-foot
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152194:24"/>of his <hi>moſt precious blood;</hi> all his <hi>fleightings, neglectings,</hi> and <hi>oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings</hi> of the Spirit of Grace, and the <hi>work</hi> of it upon his own heart, all his <hi>abuſe</hi> of <hi>Mercy,</hi> and of the <hi>Patience, forbearance,</hi> and <hi>long-ſufferings</hi> of God towards him ſhall be <hi>remembred,</hi> and ſet in ſuch order, as to give him a <hi>full view</hi> of all at once: Now how <hi>dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> muſt the <hi>very thought</hi> of this alſo needs be to an <hi>impenitent</hi> and <hi>hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted</hi> ſinner, if ever his <hi>Conſcience</hi> be but in the leaſt <hi>awakened?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, The <hi>Heart-ſinking ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation</hi> of that moſt <hi>dreadful Sentence</hi> of Condemnation to be pronounced upon him, in <hi>theſe</hi> or the <hi>like</hi> words: <hi>Go you curſed into everlaſting deſtruction, into Hell-fire, there to be tormented with the Devil and his Angels.</hi> I and to bee tormented <hi>by</hi> them, as well as <hi>with</hi> them. For the Devils ſhall not onely be <hi>companions,</hi> and <hi>ſharers</hi> with the damned Sons and Daughters of men; (or rather the Sons and Daughters of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152194:24"/>men, ſhall be <hi>ſharers with the Devil and his Angels,</hi> for whom, as for the <hi>firſt Offenders,</hi> Hell-fire is ſaid to be <hi>prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Matth.</hi> 25.41.) but ſhall alſo be their <hi>tormentors</hi> and <hi>Executioners:</hi> and what <hi>greater</hi> aggravation can there be to the <hi>miſery</hi> of <hi>Malefactors,</hi> than that thoſe that <hi>hate them most,</hi> and likewiſe have the <hi>greateſt skill,</hi> and <hi>ſtrength</hi> in inflicting torments, yea, and <hi>exceedingly delight</hi> in ſuch <hi>cruel work,</hi> and are <hi>never weary of it,</hi> ſhould be their Tormentors?</p>
               <p>Sixthly, The conſideration of a moſt <hi>ſevere</hi> and <hi>impartial Juſtice,</hi> which in caſe of <hi>non-ſatisfaction</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe made, will <hi>certainly</hi> have the <hi>ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt vengeance</hi> taken in the <hi>Execution</hi> of the aforeſaid ſentence.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, And of an <hi>utter impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility</hi> of making the <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. For who can do this, that hath <hi>no Chriſt</hi> to undertake it for him: as a Man living and dying in a ſtate of <hi>unregeneracy</hi> hath not, nor <hi>can never</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:152194:25"/>hope for it. And having <hi>no Chriſt to ſatisfie</hi> for him, ſo <hi>no Mediatour</hi> nor <hi>Advecate</hi> to ſtand betwixt God and him, to <hi>plead</hi> for him, or put in <hi>out kinde</hi> word on his behalf.</p>
               <p>Eighthly, Thereupon ſees an <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſſity</hi> of his being <hi>unſpeakably miſerable,</hi> and this too, <hi>more waies</hi> than one, (1.) By the puniſhment of <hi>leſſe.</hi> (2) By the puniſhment of <hi>ſenſe.</hi> By the <hi>puniſhment of loſſe,</hi> a <hi>tetal ſeparation</hi> from the <hi>comfortable</hi> preſence of God, and the <hi>Glory of his Power;</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.9.) I ſay, from the <hi>comfortable</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, for from his <hi>eſſential preſence</hi> none can be ſeparated, no not either <hi>men</hi> or <hi>Devils,</hi> though they <hi>make their bed in Hell.</hi> (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.8.) and then alſo by the puniſhment of <hi>ſenſe,</hi> of which I gave a touch before. In theſe two <hi>(paena damni. &amp; paena ſenſus)</hi> the puniſhment of <hi>leſſe,</hi> and the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of <hi>ſenſe,</hi> the <hi>whole torment</hi> of the damned conſiſts; and therefore in the <hi>ſentence</hi> given upon them, both
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152194:25"/>are contained, <hi>Depart from me ye curſed:</hi> There's the firſt, the puniſhment of loſs; <hi>into everlaſting Fire, prepared for the Devil and his Angels;</hi> there's the ſecond, the puniſhment of <hi>ſenſe;</hi> what this <hi>Hell-fire</hi> is we find expreſſed elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, in other <hi>terms,</hi> in <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.12. 'tis called <hi>outer darkneſs, where is weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and gnaſhing of teeth,</hi> a fire <hi>without light,</hi> which hath ſomething of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in it, but here is all darkneſs; in <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.42. 'tis called a <hi>Furnace</hi> of Fire, and <hi>wailing</hi> is there added to <hi>weeping,</hi> in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.33. The Fuel of this Fire, 'Tis ſaid to be a <hi>pile of much wood, and that the breath of the Lord like a ſtream of brimſtone doth kindle it; Rev.</hi> 14.10. 'Tis called <hi>the wine of the wrath of God, a cup of indignation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mixture;</hi> that is, 'tis <hi>pure</hi> wrath, 'tis <hi>all</hi> wrath, and <hi>nothing elſe</hi> but wrath; Juſtice without <hi>any the leaſt</hi> tincture of mercy: And 'tis <hi>poured</hi> out too, <hi>poured</hi> out, <hi>q. d.</hi> without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to note the <hi>abundance</hi> of it.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:152194:26"/>
               <p> To which, Laſtly, muſt be added that all this is <hi>eternal,</hi> 'tis <hi>everlaſting</hi> Fire, <hi>everlaſting</hi> as well as <hi>devouring Flames: everlaſting burnings!</hi> Iſa. 33.14. not onely without the leaſt hope of <hi>mitigation,</hi> or <hi>abatement,</hi> but of <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion</hi> too; When <hi>millions</hi> of <hi>milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of <hi>millions</hi> of ages are paſt, <hi>ſtill, ſtill,</hi> there is as much to come, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe 'tis an <hi>infinite</hi> puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that is due, which ſince <hi>finite</hi> Creatures can <hi>never</hi> undergo, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they do as it were <hi>compenſate</hi> by the <hi>eternity</hi> of it. Chriſt bee being an <hi>infinite perſon,</hi> could, and did ſtand under <hi>infinite wrath</hi> for thoſe he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for; and ſo God hath received <hi>full</hi> payment, his Juſtice is <hi>fully</hi> ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed for them, which it can <hi>never</hi> be by the <hi>ſufferings</hi> of the <hi>damned,</hi> to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity.</p>
               <p>Now lay <hi>all this</hi> together, and how can it do otherwiſe then miniſter moſt <hi>dreadful</hi> terrors to the minde of any unregenerate man (that is not <hi>totally</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:152194:26"/>blinded, and of a <hi>ſeared</hi> conſcience) to think of dying?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 4.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>What it is that gives a <hi>good,</hi> and <hi>ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> relief againſt the fear of death, greatly <hi>fortifying,</hi> and <hi>encouraging</hi> the heart, when it makes its approach unto it: Where firſt, the Remedy is laid down more <hi>generally.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>HAving ſpoken of thoſe things which do juſtly cauſe a very <hi>great fear</hi> and <hi>dread</hi> at the thoughts of Death: I wil now apply my ſelf to the <hi>beſt Remedies</hi> I can, againſt the ſaid fear.</p>
               <p>And the firſt and <hi>ſureſt</hi> Remedie of all, is a <hi>fundamental</hi> one, that never <hi>fails;</hi> that is, never fails of becoming a <hi>good</hi> and <hi>ſufficient</hi> ground againſt the ſaid fears: It is a <hi>true</hi> and <hi>thorow-change</hi> upon the heart, a <hi>ſaving work</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:152194:27"/>of Grace, whereby a man is <hi>regenerated</hi> and become <hi>wholly</hi> a <hi>new</hi> Creature: When a man can give <hi>good proof</hi> of this, that he is <hi>indeed tranſlated from the power of darkneſs into the Kingdome of the dear Son of God;</hi> is no longer under the <hi>power of the Prince that rules in the Air:</hi> He may then alſo <hi>truely</hi> ſay, and <hi>build</hi> upon it, that he is no <hi>Childe</hi> of Wrath, and ſo conſequently, hath <hi>no cauſe</hi> to be afraid of death; for why is <hi>death terrible</hi> to any, but for <hi>this</hi> reaſon? Among others, as we have heard, becauſe it is an <hi>inlet</hi> unto <hi>Wrath,</hi> that is, to ſuch as are <hi>Children of Wrath,</hi> but to none others: not to ſuch as are <hi>born again.</hi> For as 'tis true on the <hi>one hand,</hi> that <hi>except a man bee born again, he cannot ſee the Kingdom of God,</hi> (John 3.3.) So on the <hi>other hand,</hi> it is every whit as true, that hee that is born again, ſhall <hi>never ſee Hell,</hi> much leſs ſhall he <hi>feel it,</hi> or <hi>come into</hi> it. But then let not any man <hi>deceive</hi> himſelf, and take that for a <hi>New-birth</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:152194:27"/>which is no ſuch thing. Many <hi>preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> there are hereunto, many that wil needs paſs for the <hi>Children</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> ſuch as the <hi>ſelf-juſticiary,</hi> the <hi>civil, juſt, moral, righteous man;</hi> that <hi>harmes</hi> none, is <hi>charitable, bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent,</hi> and <hi>helpful</hi> to many; <hi>affable, courteous,</hi> and ready to <hi>do good</hi> to all, as opportunity is given him; yea, and ſeems to do what he doth <hi>chearfully,</hi> and as one <hi>glad</hi> of the occaſion, and perhaps goes <hi>further</hi> than this too, is very <hi>zealous, holy</hi> and <hi>religious</hi> in his way, keeps his <hi>Church</hi> conſtantly, and it may be <hi>prayes in his Family,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>inſtructs Children and Servants,</hi> and what not of this kinde? but if you <hi>ſearch</hi> him to the <hi>bottom;</hi> a fine ſpun <hi>Papiſt</hi> may be as good as he, his <hi>light within</hi> him, and his <hi>holy converſation</hi> without, may be no better than <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh merit;</hi> he may bee <hi>off</hi> from the <hi>foundation</hi> for all this, and bee farre enough from the <hi>true</hi> work of <hi>Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratign,</hi> and <hi>ſuch</hi> a faith and repentance
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152194:28"/>as <hi>only fits</hi> for Heaven. How <hi>many,</hi> and <hi>eſpecially</hi> in this our <hi>preſent age,</hi> have, and ſtill do, <hi>ſplit</hi> upon this <hi>Rock,</hi> in <hi>eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing their own righteouſneſs inſtead of ſubmitting to the righteouſneſs of God,</hi> as the <hi>Judaizing Chriſtians</hi> did in the Apoſtles daies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3. and for <hi>ſuch</hi> as <hi>theſe,</hi> what-ever conceits they may have of themſelves, I will not <hi>warrant</hi> them from the <hi>fear of Death,</hi> or <hi>ſecure</hi> them againſt it, their <hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> may poſſibly be <hi>better</hi> informed, concerning their <hi>inward ſtate,</hi> and then what wil follow we may eaſily gueſſe, either <hi>another</hi> more <hi>thorough</hi> work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, or <hi>ſuch terrors</hi> at the hour of death, as cannot be removed.</p>
               <p>And if any ſhall ask, How may we know when the work of <hi>regeneration</hi> is <hi>right</hi> and <hi>ſound</hi> indeed?</p>
               <p>I briefly anſwer: The Apoſtle hath given the <hi>character</hi> of it, in few words, but very <hi>fully</hi> and <hi>ſignificantly,</hi> in 2 Cor. 7.10, 11. <hi>Godly ſorrow worketh repentance to ſalvation not to be repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152194:28"/>of: For behold this ſelf-ſame thing that ye ſorrowed after a godly ſort, what carefulneſs it wrought in you; yea, what clearing of your ſelves; yea, what indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; yea, what fear; yea, what vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment deſire; yea, what zeal; yea, what revenge: In all things ye have approved your ſelves to be clear in this matter.</hi> Here are <hi>inward</hi> works, works of <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification,</hi> works of <hi>ſanctification, heart-works,</hi> ſuch as all the <hi>faculties</hi> and <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections</hi> of the ſoul are imployed in; not meer <hi>external</hi> acts, and <hi>outward for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities,</hi> without life and power: An <hi>Hypocrite</hi> may go as <hi>far</hi> in theſe <hi>ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly,</hi> yea, and farther too, than ſome <hi>ſound</hi> and <hi>ſincere-hearted</hi> Chriſtians. Look therefore into thine heart, <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine</hi> the matter there, and do it <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,</hi> without putting a <hi>cheat,</hi> or <hi>fraud</hi> upon thy ſelf, and if thou findeſt thy ſelf under <hi>this character,</hi> that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle here gives of a true penitent, then I dare pronounce thee a <hi>regenerate perſon,</hi> and one that haſt no <hi>just</hi> reaſon
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152194:29"/>to be afraid, or unwilling to dye.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 5.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Two more <hi>ſpecial remedies</hi> added to the former, <hi>viz.</hi> a <hi>reconciled</hi> God, and a <hi>good</hi> conſcience. Where firſt, of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled God.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>TO the aforeſaid <hi>general</hi> remedy, I ſhall add two <hi>ſpecial</hi> ones, which yet do more or leſſe, alwaies ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the former.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, a <hi>reconciled God,</hi> which ſpeaks much; particularly theſe five things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That <hi>Divine Justice</hi> is fully ſatisfied, <hi>ſo fully,</hi> that it can lay no <hi>farther</hi> claim; upon which God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſaies, concerning the ſoul for whom <hi>ſuch ſatisfaction</hi> is made: <hi>Deliver him, for I have found a ranſome:</hi> I am well appayed for <hi>all</hi> the <hi>wrongs</hi> hee hath done unto me, and for <hi>every debt</hi> he hath contracted.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:152194:29"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> That <hi>Gods anger</hi> is thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>appeaſed,</hi> his <hi>wrath extinguiſhed</hi> and ſo himſelf <hi>wholly pacified,</hi> and <hi>attoned:</hi> All <hi>diſpleaſure,</hi> is now gone; not an <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry word</hi> now, nor an <hi>unpleaſing look</hi> any more; <hi>And when all frowns are out of Gods face, why ſhould not all tears bee wiped from our eyes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It alwaies brings <hi>pardon</hi> with it. <hi>Reconciliation</hi> neceſſarily ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth a <hi>total removal</hi> of guilt. <hi>No charge</hi> comes in againſt <hi>that</hi> ſoul, with whom God is <hi>reconciled;</hi> nor none wil be <hi>heard</hi> againſt it; How <hi>buſie</hi> ſoever Satan is, that <hi>great accuſer</hi> of the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, yet he can do <hi>nothing</hi> now; when the <hi>Attonement</hi> is once paſt, and <hi>remiſſion</hi> obtained through the <hi>blood of Jeſus,</hi> it abides for ever; 'Tis <hi>everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> mercy, <hi>everlaſting</hi> love. As God is <hi>unchangeable</hi> in his <hi>Nature,</hi> ſo in his <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Promiſe:</hi> Hath hee made it <hi>one branch</hi> of the Covenant to <hi>pardon the iniquity</hi> of a poor penitent Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, and <hi>remember his ſin no more?
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152194:30"/>Jer.</hi> 31.34. He will be as good as his word, and the Soul that <hi>truſts</hi> him ſhall <hi>finde</hi> it ſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> By means of <hi>this</hi> the ſoul ſtands <hi>wholly blameleſs,</hi> and as 'twere, without the leaſt <hi>ſpot</hi> or <hi>wrinkle</hi> before God: 'Tis a <hi>pure</hi> and an <hi>holy</hi> Soul, ſo <hi>thoroughly waſhed</hi> by an <hi>all-cleanſing</hi> blood, (ſo 'tis called, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.7.) that <hi>no defilement</hi> remains upon it; <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing unlovely,</hi> or diſpleaſing. It is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a <hi>great beauty,</hi> as I may ſay, now, and a very <hi>taking Object</hi> in the eye of God.</p>
               <p>And thereupon, <hi>Fifthly,</hi> he takes it into his <hi>peculiar favour,</hi> and admits it into his <hi>very boſome,</hi> as his <hi>Spouſe-Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al.</hi> Queen <hi>Heſter,</hi> when firſt <hi>purified,</hi> and <hi>perfumed</hi> with the <hi>Oyle of Myrrhe,</hi> and other rich Odours (<hi>Eſth.</hi> 2.) was not <hi>more acceptable</hi> to the embraces of <hi>Ahaſhuerus,</hi> than a ſoul <hi>thus cleanſed</hi> and <hi>purified by the blood of Jeſus,</hi> and ſweetned by his <hi>precious Oyntments,</hi> is unto the <hi>God of Glory:</hi> Hee is no
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152194:30"/>
                  <hi>longer</hi> now a <hi>ſtranger,</hi> much leſs an <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy</hi> unto the ſoul, but a <hi>dear Lord,</hi> and <hi>Husband;</hi> a God in <hi>Covenant</hi> with it for ever.</p>
               <p>All which conſidered, tell me <hi>what reaſon</hi> is there, or <hi>can</hi> there be for any man to be <hi>afraid,</hi> and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>unwilling</hi> to dye, with whom God is <hi>thus reconciled?</hi> Sure none at all. And this is the firſt <hi>ſpecial</hi> Remedy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 6.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of a good Conſcience, which is the ſecond <hi>ſpecial Remedy,</hi> and wherein it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts: It hath two branches; 'tis a <hi>quiet</hi> Conſcience, and an <hi>excuſing</hi> Conſcience; a quiet Conſcience, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts alſo in two things; <hi>(1.)</hi> In a ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and <hi>well-grounded</hi> peace. <hi>(2.)</hi> In being <hi>void of offence,</hi> both towards God, and towards men. Where of the firſt.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Come now to the ſecond ſpecial Remedy, <hi>a good Conſcience,</hi> which
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152194:31"/>doth likewiſe much fortifie againſt the fear of Death. I ſhall not here ſpeak of Conſcience at large, neither of its <hi>Nature,</hi> nor ſeveral <hi>operations,</hi> nor enquire whether it be properly an <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit,</hi> as <hi>Scotus, Bonaventure,</hi> and <hi>Duran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> with other <hi>Schoolmen,</hi> would have it, but onely briefly lay down a few things, for the right underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Then it may be thus deſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. It is the <hi>judgement of a man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning himſelf, as it is ſubjected to the judgement of God</hi> the ſupream Judge; and is that which God himſelf, as I may ſo ſay, appeals to, (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.3.) <hi>Judge, I pray, betwixt me and my Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard.</hi> So, 1 Cor. 11.31. <hi>If we would judge our ſelves, we ſhould not be judged,</hi> And</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> 'Tis ſaid to be a good Conſcience, when it judgeth <hi>rightly,</hi> and according to the <hi>Word</hi> of God, which alone both <hi>directs</hi> and <hi>bindes</hi> it; Thus it is, <hi>honeſtè bona,</hi> good in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152194:31"/>of the honeſty and integrity of it, when it accuſeth or excuſeth <hi>right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and according to <hi>truth;</hi> and this in all the actions of a man's life, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good or bad: For in Conſcience are two things, by which it is enabled to make a judgement of its <hi>own Acts.</hi> (1.) That which Divines call <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a <hi>treaſury</hi> of Knowledge, in which the Notions of things to be done, or not to be done, are as 'twere kept and conſerved. (2.) That which is called <hi>judicium practicum,</hi> or rather the act of a practical judgement, proceeding from the underſtanding faculty, which is the <hi>chief ſeat</hi> of Conſcience; and becauſe it alone next to God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf knows its <hi>own act,</hi> and none elſe, therefore the knowledge of it is called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a <hi>con-knowledge,</hi> as I may ſo ſay, or a knowledge in <hi>combination</hi> with Gods knowledge, which hee hath of man, and of his actions, as o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Learned Perkins</hi> expreſſeth it, whom <hi>Ameſius</hi> follows.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:152194:32"/>
               <p> But to ſay no more about this, but what the Apoſtle doth, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.20. <hi>If our heart condemn us, God is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than our heart, and knoweth all things.</hi> I proceed to ſpeak of a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as it is, <hi>pacatè bona,</hi> a <hi>quiet Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience;</hi> of which there are two branches, wherein it doth conſiſt.</p>
               <p>The firſt is a <hi>ſettled</hi> and <hi>well-groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> peace: It is not any kinde of peace, a <hi>ſleight</hi> and <hi>unſound</hi> peace, that makes a <hi>quiet</hi> conſcience, or can give ſuch a <hi>reſt</hi> and <hi>complacency</hi> unto it, as to cauſe it to become a <hi>Nightingale</hi> in a mans own boſome, and that in the time of the <hi>greateſt diſtreſs</hi> that can befal him in this world: No, but it is a <hi>firm</hi> and <hi>ſollid</hi> peace that muſt, that can, do this and no other.</p>
               <p>Now that I may be the better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood what I mean by ſuch a <hi>ſollid, firm, ſettled,</hi> and <hi>well-grounded</hi> peace, as conſtitutes a <hi>quiet Conſcience,</hi> that is at peace within it ſelf, and makes its <hi>own Muſick;</hi> whatever <hi>clamours</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152194:32"/>may be round about it; I ſhall lay down ſeveral things, to which it bears a <hi>faithful witneſs,</hi> and of which it hath <hi>clear</hi> and <hi>ſatisfying</hi> evidences within it ſelf: in which ſenſe it is that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.14. where he ſaith, <hi>that a good man is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied from himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt Then, a <hi>quiet Conſcience,</hi> and ſetled in ſuch a firm peace as aforeſaid, bears witneſs to this, that it hath <hi>truly</hi> and <hi>ſavingly cloſed</hi> with Jeſus Chriſt, and this by a <hi>double act;</hi> an act of <hi>faith</hi> and an act of <hi>love:</hi> By an <hi>act</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> conſidering him as <hi>Chriſt-Crucified;</hi> in which ſenſe moſt properly hee is the <hi>next</hi> and <hi>immediate</hi> object of Faith; And by an <hi>act</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> conſidering him as a moſt <hi>excellent</hi> and <hi>lovely</hi> perſon; In which ſenſe properly he is the <hi>high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt object</hi> of our <hi>love;</hi> for 'tis <hi>amabile,</hi> ſomething <hi>lovely,</hi> that is moſt proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>objectum amoris,</hi> the object of love. Now when Conſcience gives e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of ſuch a <hi>double cloſure</hi> with
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152194:33"/>Jeſus Chriſt, both as a <hi>Prince, and a Saviour;</hi> as a dying <hi>Mediatour,</hi> and a dear <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Husband;</hi> and that it hath not onely done this for <hi>once,</hi> as I may ſo ſay, but <hi>continues</hi> to do this alwaies, by <hi>new acts</hi> of Faith, and Love, by <hi>repeated acts</hi> every day, and ſo is <hi>alwaies</hi> united to him, hath and doth <hi>alwaies</hi> accept him, is as 'twere, <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies embracing</hi> him, and <hi>cleaving</hi> to him, and that as <hi>heartily,</hi> and <hi>affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately,</hi> as ever a <hi>pleaſed Bride</hi> did to, and with her <hi>beloved Bridegroom;</hi> and that it hath taken him, and <hi>ever</hi> doth take him, as <hi>God gives him,</hi> with all his <hi>Offices</hi> and <hi>Powers</hi> over the Soul; as <hi>King, Prieſt</hi> and <hi>Prophet,</hi> to be taught, and ruled, as wel as ſaved by him. I ſay, when Conſcience <hi>bears witneſs</hi> to this, and hath an <hi>undoubted</hi> and <hi>clear</hi> proof of this within it ſelf: What <hi>greater foundation</hi> can it lay for its own peace and quiet? For doth not peace come in by believing? The Apoſtle ſaith it doth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.13. and indeed,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152194:33"/>where is <hi>ſuch</hi> a peace to be had, a peace <hi>ſo ſweet</hi> and <hi>ſatisfying,</hi> as a ſoul enjoyes that hath contracted a <hi>friendſhip,</hi> a <hi>great</hi> and <hi>intimate friendſhip,</hi> between <hi>Chriſt</hi> and it <hi>ſelf?</hi> Now this, every <hi>believing</hi> ſoul doth, every <hi>true lover</hi> of Chriſt, that cloſeth with him by ſuch a <hi>double act</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> as hath been now mentioned; For doth not ſuch a cloſure: (1.) Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily make an <hi>union</hi> betwixt Chriſt and the ſoul, a <hi>ſtrict, firm,</hi> and <hi>entire union?</hi> And where ſuch an <hi>union</hi> is, doth not <hi>communion</hi> follow too? <hi>Sweet</hi> and <hi>bleſſed communion,</hi> for doth not <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Soul now live</hi> in each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>boſomes?</hi> Is there any more than <hi>one heart,</hi> as it were, between them? Eſpouſals when finiſhed give <hi>more than co-habitation</hi> here, more than a meer dwelling together; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a <hi>mutual in-dwelling</hi> in each other; the <hi>Soul</hi> in the very <hi>boſome,</hi> and <hi>heart</hi> of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> only, in the ſoul. So ſaies the Apoſtle,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152194:34"/>
                  <hi>Chriſt in you the hope of Glory,</hi> Col. 1.27. <hi>And if any man be in Chriſt, he is a new Creature;</hi> 2 Cor. 5.17. And can there be ſo ſweet a peace then, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny where as here?</p>
               <p>Secondly, When Conſcience bears <hi>farther witneſs,</hi> that as it hath cloſed thus with <hi>Crucified Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>lovely Chriſt,</hi> in his perſon, ſo that it hath done as God himſelf doth, <hi>laid all its ſins upon Christs back,</hi> transferred all thither, <hi>tranſpoſed</hi> them all from its <hi>own back</hi> to <hi>his,</hi> who is <hi>beſt able</hi> to bear them, yea, who <hi>alone</hi> can bear <hi>them,</hi> and the <hi>wrath</hi> of God due to them. Compare <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.6. with 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21. Where 'tis ſaid, that <hi>God hath laid upon him the iniquity of us all;</hi> that is, of all that believe; and that <hi>he hath made him to be ſin for us:</hi> What elſe did the <hi>ſlain Goat</hi> which was offered up <hi>for all the ſins and unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the children of</hi> Iſrael, ſignifie, <hi>Levit.</hi> 16.7, 15, 16. and the <hi>live-Goat</hi> over whoſe head, <hi>all the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152194:34"/>of the Children of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and all their tranſgreſſions in their ſins</hi> were confeſſed, and upon whoſe <hi>head</hi> they were all put, and he ſent away <hi>into the Wilderneſs;</hi> or, as ſome ſay, into the land of <hi>forgetfulneſs,</hi> verſe 21, 22. I ſay, what did they both ſignifie but <hi>this,</hi> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is he, whom theſe <hi>two Goats</hi> typifyed, <hi>Chriſt onely,</hi> that <hi>bears</hi> our ſins, <hi>dyes</hi> for them, and <hi>carries</hi> them away, ſo as they never come into <hi>remembrance</hi> any more; and that he was <hi>anti-type</hi> to <hi>both</hi> theſe Goates, and that in <hi>this reſpect only,</hi> is evident in the New Teſtament, firſt to the <hi>ſlain Goat,</hi> therefore is called, the <hi>Lamb ſlain, Rev.</hi> 5.6, 9. and alſo to the <hi>ſcape-Goat,</hi> therefore ſaid to bee <hi>the Lamb of God that taketh away,</hi> (or bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth away; ſo 'tis in the Margent, in the Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>the ſins of the world, John</hi> 1.29. Upon <hi>him</hi> then it is, that every <hi>true Believer</hi> lays all his ſins, and that even <hi>every day,</hi> as faſt as he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits them, brings <hi>new loads, new bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:152194:35"/>to Chriſts back; all his <hi>new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted guilts,</hi> and were not Chriſt <hi>mighty</hi> to <hi>bear,</hi> as well as <hi>mighty</hi> to <hi>ſave;</hi> how could he ſtand under <hi>ſuch encreaſing weights?</hi> And from <hi>ſo many</hi> hands too, that <hi>continually</hi> lay load upon him? For doth not a <hi>true Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> and right improver of Chriſt Crucified, every day, do <hi>two things,</hi> bring ſomething <hi>to Chriſt,</hi> and fetch ſomething <hi>from him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt <hi>he brings</hi> ſomething to Chriſt. What's that you'l ſay? Why hee brings both his <hi>worſt,</hi> and his <hi>beſt</hi> to Chriſt. His <hi>worſt,</hi> that is, his <hi>ſins,</hi> and laies them on <hi>Chriſts back;</hi> his <hi>beſt,</hi> and that is, his <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>affections</hi> in all the Services he performs to him.</p>
               <p>And then <hi>fetcheth</hi> ſomething from him every day; and if you ask what that is? I anſwer, nothing but <hi>his All;</hi> all his <hi>Pardons,</hi> all his <hi>Comforts;</hi> all manner of <hi>ſupplies</hi> from his <hi>rich ſtores; ſtrength</hi> againſt his <hi>Corruptions</hi> and <hi>Temptations;</hi> abilities for the Exerciſe
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152194:35"/>of every Grace, and Performance of every Duty. Now then if Conſcience bears witneſs to <hi>this too,</hi> is not here new matter of peace ſtill?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, When Conſcience bears witneſs, that ſince the ſoul hath come into <hi>Chriſts arms,</hi> and <hi>transferred</hi> all its ſins upon his back; it hath alſo <hi>array<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> it ſelf with <hi>his Robes,</hi> his Robes of Righteouſneſs; that the <hi>ſame Faith</hi> which <hi>united</hi> it to his <hi>Perſon,</hi> hath <hi>put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> his <hi>Ornaments;</hi> and ſo is not only <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to him, but <hi>wears</hi> him, and is thereby become <hi>beautiful</hi> and <hi>glorious;</hi> Beautiful with his <hi>Beauty and comeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which he hath put upon it, Ezek.</hi> 16.14. with thoſe <hi>Garments</hi> of <hi>Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> which he hath now cloathed it with, and all be-deck'd it, <hi>as a Bride is decked with Jewels, Iſa.</hi> 61.10. for how <hi>tattered</hi> and <hi>terne</hi> ſoever a poor ſoul be, before 'tis <hi>eſpouſed</hi> to Chriſt, yet when <hi>that day</hi> once comes, <hi>that bleſſed</hi> day of all others, 'tis in <hi>rags</hi> no longer, but puts on its <hi>Robes of ſtate.</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:152194:36"/>When <hi>Salomons Queen</hi> ſtands by him, ſhe ſtands there <hi>like her ſelf,</hi> as one made meet to be his Queen, <hi>in gold of</hi> Ophir, <hi>and cloathing of wrought Gold. Pſal.</hi> 45.9, 13. So doth poor <hi>captive Heſter,</hi> when taken out of her <hi>captive-condition,</hi> and made <hi>Queen,</hi> ſhe throws away her <hi>captive-weeds,</hi> and comes to her <hi>Liege-Lord</hi> and <hi>Prince,</hi> with the <hi>Crown Royal upon her head,</hi> and in <hi>robes of Majeſty;</hi> though all ſtill, not at her <hi>own coſt</hi> or <hi>charges,</hi> or by her <hi>own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curement,</hi> but by <hi>free-gift</hi> from her <hi>gracious Prince,</hi> who finding <hi>love e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough</hi> in his <hi>heart</hi> to make her his <hi>Queen,</hi> found <hi>money enough</hi> in his <hi>Coffers</hi> thus <hi>richly</hi> to <hi>adorn</hi> her. And thus is it here between Chriſt and the Soul; he provides it <hi>ſumptuous attire</hi> and the ſoul by <hi>Faith</hi> puts it on, and Oh! now <hi>how lovely</hi> and <hi>taking</hi> is it in the eye of Chriſt? what a <hi>goodly</hi> perſon is it? How doth it <hi>dazle</hi> in it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Cloath of Gold!</hi> and in <hi>ſuch</hi> a cloat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Gold as is <hi>Coat of Male</hi> too, which
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152194:36"/>
                  <hi>Divine Juſtice</hi> it ſelf with its <hi>keeneſt</hi> Arrows can <hi>never pierce;</hi> all which, while Conſcience hath an <hi>evidence</hi> of, within it ſelf, and can <hi>prove</hi> that it hath thus <hi>put on Chriſt;</hi> Is not here alſo <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother</hi> ground of <hi>peace?</hi> of <hi>admirable peace?</hi> Yes verily, ſaies the Apoſtle, Rom. 5.1. <hi>Being juſtified by Faith we have peace with God, through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, When Conſcience bears witneſs, that 'tis not content onely with the <hi>meere work of Regeneration,</hi> and that it hath indeed paſſed that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, whereby it is become a <hi>Childe,</hi> as well of the <hi>ſecond Adam,</hi> as of the <hi>firſt;</hi> and bears the <hi>Image,</hi> as of the <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> man, ſo of the <hi>Heavenly</hi> too; but alſo, is every day endeavouring to <hi>perfect holineſs in the fear of God,</hi> and to be <hi>growing in Grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt;</hi> and ſo, more and more <hi>making ſure</hi> of Heaven; according as the Apoſtle excellently diſcourſeth,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152194:37"/>in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5,—9. <hi>For ſo,</hi> ſays he, <hi>An en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance ſhall be miniſtred unto you abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly into the everlaſting Kingdome of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> So, how? why, by <hi>giving all diligence to adde to Faith, Virtue; and to Virtue, Knowledge;</hi> and ſo of the reſt: that is, to add <hi>new degrees</hi> to every Grace, for otherwiſe, there is <hi>no new Grace</hi> can be added, that was not received in the <hi>first work,</hi> when the ſoul was <hi>firſt regenerated</hi> and became a <hi>new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> The meaning therefore is, that he is not ſatisfied with <hi>meere habitual</hi> Grace; but is careful that every grace may <hi>grow,</hi> and <hi>grow</hi> at <hi>root,</hi> and <hi>branch</hi> too, in <hi>fairneſs, ſweetneſs, fragrancy:</hi> He would not have the <hi>earthly plants</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in his Garden, <hi>out-grow</hi> the <hi>Heavenly</hi> ones that are in his heart; he would not have the <hi>Sun, Showers,</hi> and <hi>Influences</hi> of the <hi>viſible</hi> Heavens, fall <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> upon his <hi>Violets</hi> and his <hi>Roſes,</hi> than the <hi>powerful Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> and <hi>Influences</hi> of the <hi>Sun</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> upon his
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:152194:37"/>
                  <hi>Soul;</hi> and therefore he <hi>takes pains</hi> with his own heart, waits upon <hi>every Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance,</hi> improves every <hi>opportunity</hi> he meets with, <hi>ſeeks all waies</hi> and means, and uſeth all <hi>poſsible endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours</hi> that he may <hi>thrive</hi> in his <hi>inward</hi> man, and at laſt attain to that <hi>ſtature</hi> in Chriſt, that may render him <hi>meet to partake of the inheritance of the Saints in light;</hi> However others ſpend their time in this world, this is one of his <hi>main buſineſſes,</hi> and this his Conſcience bears him witneſs; and is not here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain <hi>more matter</hi> of peace?</p>
               <p>Fifthly, when Conſcience bears witneſs to a man, that to the <hi>utmoſt</hi> of his power, he hath <hi>faithfully</hi> diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>all relative</hi> duties that lye upon him; either as a <hi>good ſubject</hi> to his ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours, and the powers he lives un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as far as may any way <hi>conſiſt</hi> with his <hi>loyalty</hi> to Jeſus Chriſt, or in his <hi>domeſtick</hi> relations in his family, as an <hi>Husband,</hi> a <hi>Father,</hi> a <hi>Maſter;</hi> or as a <hi>Childe,</hi> a <hi>Servant;</hi> or what ever o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:152194:38"/>Family-<hi>Relation,</hi> he or ſhe hath ſtood in; or as related to a <hi>Church</hi> of Chriſt, of which happily he is a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; or to any other of his <hi>fellow-Saints</hi> abroad, or <hi>Neighbours, Dealers, Traders,</hi> with whom he any way con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeth. I ſay, when Conſcience <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth</hi> for no want of duty here like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; It is a <hi>quiet</hi> Conſcience, and at peace within it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, When Conſcience bears a man witneſs that he hath been, or, at leaſt, is of a <hi>God-like Spirit,</hi> that is, of a <hi>gracious</hi> and <hi>benigne</hi> Diſpoſition. (1.) To all men in general. That as <hi>his Sun ſhines both upon the Juſt, and unjuſt; and his Rain falls on good and evil; Matth.</hi> 5.45. So he hath been, and alwaies is <hi>ready,</hi> as occaſion ſerves, to do good to <hi>all ſorts</hi> of men, even the very <hi>worſt</hi> that are, ſo far as may <hi>conſiſt</hi> with the <hi>Rule</hi> of his Duty, and he hath any <hi>warrant</hi> for it. But more eſpecially towards <hi>three ſorts</hi> of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the World. (1.) To <hi>Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152194:38"/>Enemies,</hi> ſuch as hate him, have much offended him, and done him wrong; yet hath been alwaies ready to <hi>lay aſide revenge,</hi> and to <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and <hi>forgive,</hi> even to <hi>ſeventy times ſeven:</hi> Thus God doth, and thus his Conſcience bears him witneſs, 'tis his not onely endeavour, but <hi>delight</hi> to do; even to <hi>overcome evil with good.</hi> (2.) To perſons <hi>in miſery,</hi> he is like God here too, of a <hi>merciful</hi> diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; can ſay as <hi>Job,</hi> yea, and <hi>appeal</hi> to God himſelf, as he did, concerning his <hi>compaſsion</hi> and <hi>helpfulneſs</hi> to the <hi>Widdow,</hi> the <hi>Fatherleſs,</hi> the <hi>poor,</hi> and the <hi>oppreſſed,</hi> that had no friend to ſpeak for them in <hi>the Gate;</hi> No <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels</hi> to feed upon, nor <hi>Garments</hi> to wear, but what they received from <hi>his Table, Bounty,</hi> or <hi>Procurement, Job</hi> 31.16-22. (3.) But <hi>moſt</hi> of all to the <hi>poor ſuffering Members</hi> of Jeſus Chriſt; to them, of all others, his <hi>Bowels yearne;</hi> them, to be ſure, he will not fail to <hi>relieve, cheriſh, viſit, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:152194:39"/>and every way, <hi>as far as able,</hi> miniſter unto them, and this without <hi>diſtinction</hi> of Perſons, or Parties; 'tis not <hi>this,</hi> or <hi>that</hi> difference in Opinion, (provided it be ſuch as leaves a man upon the foundation) but the <hi>grace</hi> of Chriſt, that <hi>draws</hi> his <hi>heart,</hi> and his <hi>compaſsions</hi> from him.</p>
               <p>Seventhly and laſtly, When Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience yet farther bears witneſs, that in all, he hath <hi>purely ſought</hi> the <hi>glory</hi> of God; even in <hi>all</hi> that he hath done, throughout his <hi>whole</hi> courſe, in one kinde or another; yea, and that he hath not onely been ready to do what <hi>Service</hi> he could for God, in <hi>any capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city</hi> wherein he hath at any time ſet him, ſince he had any <hi>ſaving know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of him, but hath been ready alſo to <hi>ſuffer for him,</hi> and give <hi>teſtimony</hi> to his <hi>Truths, Waies, Ordinances,</hi> and holy <hi>Inſtitutions,</hi> in oppoſition to what-ever hath been <hi>contrary</hi> unto them: What-ever <hi>Sufferings</hi> of his, might any way <hi>advance</hi> Chriſt his
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:152194:39"/>
                  <hi>Name, Honor,</hi> and <hi>Intereſt</hi> in the world, he hath <hi>willingly undergone</hi> them, and ſtill is ready, as much as in him lies, in all <hi>lawful</hi> and <hi>warrantable</hi> waies to do his utmoſt for the <hi>raiſing</hi> of Chriſt and his Kingdome <hi>higher and higher,</hi> even above the <hi>Thrones</hi> and <hi>Scepters</hi> of all that oppoſe him. If Chriſt might <hi>aſcend</hi> but one <hi>inch</hi> by his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming a <hi>foot-ſtool</hi> to him, he would <hi>joy</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> in it; he cares not <hi>how much hee decreaſeth, ſo Chriſt may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe:</hi> No proud ambitious <hi>Haman</hi> ever ſought his <hi>own honour,</hi> ſo much as he <hi>ſeeks Chriſts;</hi> his <hi>heart,</hi> his <hi>whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heart,</hi> is ſet upon this; his <hi>time,</hi> his <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,</hi> his <hi>parts,</hi> his <hi>power,</hi> and <hi>intereſt</hi> among men (if any he hath) <hi>all</hi> ſhall be improved <hi>this way,</hi> to ſerve Chriſt; let his <hi>ſufferings</hi> be what they will, or can be; in his <hi>Name, Liberty,</hi> bodily <hi>Pains;</hi> no <hi>Priſons</hi> ſcare him, no <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows</hi> whatever, ſo Chriſt may <hi>gain</hi> by it. Now when Conſcience bears wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to <hi>this</hi> alſo, as well as to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:152194:40"/>particulars, that <hi>this</hi> is the <hi>frame</hi> of his heart, or, at leaſt, that he <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely deſires</hi> and <hi>endeavours</hi> that it may be ſo: this man, I dare <hi>avouch</hi> hath a <hi>quiet</hi> Conſcience, a Conſcience <hi>ſettled</hi> in a <hi>well-grounded peace,</hi> and ſo hath no <hi>juſt reaſon</hi> to fear death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 7.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The ſecond Branch of a quiet Conſcience, namely, a Conſcience void of offence both towards God and towards men.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>A Conſcience <hi>void of offence</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, is a Conſcience <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling</hi> and <hi>putting</hi> a man upon his <hi>ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt</hi> endeavours, in <hi>all things,</hi> to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it ſelf to God; and to walk be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>unto all pleaſing, Col.</hi> 1.10. Which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaies, is to <hi>walk,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>Worthy of the Lord,</hi> who in all things <hi>deſerves</hi> to be pleaſed by his <hi>own Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:152194:40"/>eſpecially by <hi>man</hi> above the reſt, for whom he hath done <hi>more</hi> than for <hi>all</hi> the reſt, more than for <hi>Angels</hi> themſelves. Now he that upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration thereof doth all he can to teſtifie his <hi>gratitude</hi> to his moſt <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging</hi> God, in avoiding <hi>every thing</hi> that may offend him, not onely <hi>every ſin,</hi> but <hi>every occaſion</hi> unto ſin, <hi>every ſhadow</hi> of it, and ſo hates the <hi>very garment ſpotted of the fleſh;</hi> and alſo in doing whatever may be <hi>acceptable</hi> and <hi>delightful</hi> to him; <hi>this man,</hi> if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, hath a Conſcience <hi>void of offence</hi> towards God. For to be ſure he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies doth <hi>three things,</hi> that none elſe do.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> He makes it his <hi>great care</hi> and <hi>ſtudy,</hi> to finde out the <hi>whole will</hi> of God concerning him, to underſtand <hi>all</hi> his Duty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> To <hi>practice all</hi> that hee knows thereof, even to his <hi>utmoſt;</hi> So that <hi>God himſelf</hi> may <hi>ſay</hi> of him, as he did of his Servant <hi>David, Act.</hi> 13.22.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:152194:41"/>
                  <hi>I have found</hi> David, <hi>my Servant, a man after mine own heart, he ſhall do</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>all my wills;</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>herein lies</hi> the very <hi>excellency</hi> of our obedience, that 'tis done in <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with,</hi> and purſuance of, the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Will,</hi> and to have our <hi>own wills engaged</hi> in ſo doing: for as 'tis the <hi>will</hi> in God, that an holy man <hi>chiefly</hi> looks at, as the <hi>ground</hi> and <hi>great reaſon</hi> of his obedience; ſo 'tis the <hi>will</hi> in man that <hi>God</hi> alſo <hi>chiefly</hi> eyes in all he doth: If there be, firſt (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>a willing minde,</hi> ſayes the Apoſtle, <hi>it is accepted,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.12. Intimating that if <hi>this</hi> be wanting, let the Duty in the <hi>matter</hi> of it, or ſeeming <hi>perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance</hi> otherwiſe, be never ſo <hi>ſplendid</hi> and <hi>glorious,</hi> yet 'tis not accepted. 'Twill be no better than a <hi>guilded ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> as the Lord ſaies to <hi>Judah</hi> by the mouth of the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> Chap. 2.22. (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas tua inaurata</hi>) 'tis but a <hi>fine painted ſin,</hi> when all is done. We ſay in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:152194:41"/>
                  <hi>forma dat eſſe,</hi> 'tis not the <hi>matter,</hi> but the <hi>form</hi> that <hi>ſpecificates</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing, and <hi>diſtinguiſheth</hi> it from all things elſe; it is much more true in <hi>Divinity;</hi> the <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>Soul</hi> of the man muſt be in every act of <hi>that obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> which pleaſeth God, he muſt be <hi>ſincere</hi> in it, and that <hi>univerſally,</hi> and <hi>conſtantly,</hi> every command muſt bee <hi>readily</hi> embraced, and <hi>gladly</hi> obeyed, and he that doth this, or at leaſt, <hi>ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſires,</hi> and <hi>endeavours</hi> it, is upright <hi>before,</hi> and acceptable to <hi>God;</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, it being added in the</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Third</hi> place, that wherein he <hi>fails,</hi> 'tis the <hi>great grief</hi> and <hi>ſorrow</hi> of his heart; that which coſts him <hi>many</hi> a <hi>ſigh,</hi> in ſecret, and <hi>many</hi> a <hi>tear</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and him: and this briefly is to have a <hi>Conſcience void of offence towards God,</hi> and concerning which, he can <hi>appeal</hi> to God, as <hi>Job</hi> did, whatever men ſay, or think of him, (<hi>Job</hi> 16.19, 20.) <hi>Alſo now my wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is in Heaven, and my Record is on
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:152194:42"/>high, my friends ſcorn me, but mine eye poureth out tears unto God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next thing is, That 'tis a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience <hi>void of offence towards men too.</hi> When is that you'l ſay? When there is a great <hi>tenderneſs</hi> in the Conſcience, of doing <hi>wrong</hi> to any, no not in the leaſt; and a <hi>great impulſe</hi> to do to <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man</hi> what is <hi>right</hi> and <hi>juſt;</hi> and this from a <hi>principle</hi> of <hi>holineſs:</hi> For <hi>holineſs</hi> towards God is the <hi>root</hi> upon which <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> towards men ſtands, and from <hi>whence</hi> only it <hi>ſprings</hi> and <hi>grows.</hi> And the truth is, without <hi>both</hi> theſe, Conſcience <hi>cannot be good,</hi> neither as a <hi>light,</hi> nor as a <hi>witneſs,</hi> nor as a <hi>Judge;</hi> It can perform none of its <hi>Offices</hi> in <hi>fit</hi> manner, nor <hi>due</hi> order: the rule holds here, as much as any where, <hi>ad conſtituendum bonum, ponenda ſunt omnia requiſita, ſed malum fit ex quolibet defectu:</hi> to conſtitute a good thing, all requiſites muſt be preſent, but one defect onely makes it evil: Therefore the Apoſtle, when he would deſcribe a
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:152194:42"/>
                  <hi>good</hi> Conſcience, puts in <hi>comprehenſive words,</hi> words that take all in, that ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it <hi>every way</hi> good, <hi>Honestè bona, &amp; pacatè bona,</hi> good in the <hi>integrity</hi> of it, good in the <hi>calmneſs</hi> and <hi>peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs</hi> of it. <hi>Void of offence!</hi> How <hi>large</hi> is that? and void of offence <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God!</hi> how <hi>large</hi> is that too? What needed hee have added any more? The truth is, whoever <hi>offends men,</hi> and <hi>himſelf,</hi> among others; who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever interrupts his <hi>own peace,</hi> brings any <hi>guilt</hi> upon his <hi>own Soul,</hi> as well as doth <hi>wrong</hi> to another, doth he not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>therein</hi> alſo <hi>offend God,</hi> and <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs</hi> his Law: However, the Apoſtle notwithſtanding adds that alſo, <hi>Void of offence towards men,</hi> and thought it <hi>neceſſary</hi> to do ſo, not onely for the more <hi>full vindication</hi> of himſelf before the <hi>Roman Governours,</hi> to whom hee appealed; but to intimate that his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions were every way ſuch, that hee durſt <hi>appeal</hi> even to <hi>men</hi> alſo, whoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they were, though enemies, as
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:152194:43"/>well as a <hi>righteous God,</hi> if they would but be <hi>impartial,</hi> and lay aſide <hi>paſsion,</hi> and <hi>prejudice,</hi> that he was <hi>unjuſtly</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed.</p>
               <p>But this by the way onely; Let's conſider what the Apoſtle means in this place, by a <hi>Conſcience void of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence towards men;</hi> I conceive he doth not place it in <hi>meere moral</hi> acts of juſtice, ſuch as <hi>fair dealing,</hi> paying e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man his <hi>own,</hi> giving every man his <hi>due,</hi> and ſuch like, but in a <hi>pious,</hi> and <hi>religious</hi> care, no way to become an <hi>offence,</hi> a <hi>ſtumbling-block,</hi> or <hi>ſcandal</hi> to any, by any <hi>dangerous opinion,</hi> or <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil example;</hi> and that this is the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles <hi>ſenſe,</hi> or at leaſt his <hi>principal meaning,</hi> two things induce me to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve. (1.) What hee ſaies in the fore-going verſes, (14, 15) where he ſpeaks of the <hi>ſoundneſs</hi> of his <hi>Faith, believing all things that are written in the Law and the Prophets;</hi> and of the <hi>holineſs</hi> of his <hi>practiſe,</hi> in a pure and <hi>right worſhipping of the God of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:152194:43"/>to both which he immediately ſubjoyns this his <hi>double exerciſe</hi> of a good Conſcience, or a <hi>Conſcience void of offence both towards God, and towards men.</hi> (2.) The Annotation of the Greek word (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) tranſlated <hi>void of offence;</hi> properly ſignifying one that doth not cauſe another to <hi>ſtumble,</hi> for ſo this very word is uſed in <hi>Luke</hi> 4.11. For <hi>daſhing ones foot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a ſtone</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) when <hi>Balaam</hi> taught <hi>Balak</hi> how to bring <hi>Iſrael</hi> into ſin, by <hi>Whoredome</hi> and <hi>Idolatry,</hi> 'tis ſaid (<hi>Rev.</hi> 2.14.) <hi>he taught him to caſt</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>a stumbling-block before the Children of</hi> Iſrael. <hi>Heſychius, Eſtius, Beza, Grotius,</hi> and many other <hi>learned</hi> men <hi>criticize</hi> upon this word <hi>variouſly,</hi> but all in <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> amounts to this, when a man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes an <hi>occaſion</hi> to his Neighbour, <hi>any way to ſin,</hi> he is then a <hi>ſcandal,</hi> a <hi>ſtone</hi> of offence, a <hi>Trap, Gin,</hi> or <hi>Snare</hi> to him, and is guilty of the <hi>curſe</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced (in <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.14.) upon thoſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:152194:44"/>that <hi>lay ſtumbling-blocks before the blinde.</hi> Now hee that by all means takes heed of this, as well in things <hi>Spiritual,</hi> as otherwiſe, hee it is that <hi>moſt truely</hi> may be ſaid to have <hi>a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience void of offence towards men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus have I done with the firſt <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral</hi> Branch, of a good Conſcience, a <hi>quiet</hi> Conſcience. I come to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 8.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of an Excuſing Conſcience, which makes its own defence, <hi>(1.)</hi> Against the Challenge of exacting Juſtice; <hi>(2.)</hi> Againſt the malice of an accuſing De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Will begin with the firſt, The <hi>Challenge of Exacting Juſtice;</hi> What is that <hi>Challenge,</hi> you'l ſay? Why it <hi>challengeth</hi> for the <hi>breach</hi> of the <hi>whole Law of God;</hi> and this a <hi>thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:152194:44"/>and a <hi>thouſand</hi> times over, for <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold</hi> and <hi>great</hi> wrongs done to God; beſides ſuch, as an abuſe of his <hi>patience, forbearance</hi> and <hi>long-ſufferance,</hi> great and high <hi>ingratitudes,</hi> for many <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> received; <hi>non-improvements</hi> of the means of Grace, with many other crimes of like nature, but eſpecially for <hi>Goſpel-ſins,</hi> and the <hi>neglects</hi> of thoſe offers, which, for a <hi>long time</hi> were made, before ever they were at all <hi>regarded,</hi> or <hi>hearkned</hi> to; For all which, <hi>Juſtice</hi> crys out to the <hi>God of Justice,</hi> againſt the <hi>Sinner;</hi> calls for <hi>ſatisfaction,</hi> and that to the <hi>utmoſt far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> both <hi>principal</hi> and <hi>intereſt:</hi> or elſe, away let him go, <hi>ſaies Juſtice;</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with him to <hi>Priſon,</hi> to Hell-fire, there let him lie, and there let him be <hi>puniſhed too,</hi> according to the <hi>merits</hi> of the cauſe; <hi>ſpare him not,</hi> ſays Juſtice: let him know what it is to ſin againſt <hi>ſuch a God,</hi> and abuſe <hi>ſuch Mercy</hi> as he hath abuſed. This, and <hi>abundance more</hi> hath Juſtice to ſay, even againſt
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:152194:45"/>the <hi>beſt</hi> man and woman in the world.</p>
               <p>To all which an <hi>excuſing Conſcience</hi> makes anſwer, and <hi>defends</hi> it ſelf thus, by pleading three things, againſt which even <hi>Juſtice</hi> it ſelf can make <hi>no reply,</hi> but is left <hi>wholly ſpeechleſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Acknowledgeth that <hi>Juſtice</hi> is juſt in its <hi>Challenge;</hi> that it <hi>ſelf</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the <hi>perſon</hi> guilty of all this; of all theſe <hi>debts,</hi> and theſe <hi>crimes;</hi> but withal, that both the <hi>debt,</hi> and the <hi>guilt</hi> is <hi>transferred,</hi> and that Juſtice it ſelf muſt <hi>herein</hi> be juſt alſo, in mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its <hi>challenge</hi> where the <hi>debt</hi> and the <hi>guilt</hi> lies, which is not now upon <hi>me,</hi> ſaies Conſcience, but upon <hi>Chriſt my ſurety,</hi> who hath <hi>undertaken</hi> for me: my <hi>gracious God</hi> hath <hi>laid all my ſins upon his back,</hi> and my <hi>gracious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer</hi> was <hi>willing</hi> he ſhould; and <hi>thither,</hi> I alſo have carried them, and <hi>laid</hi> them too.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſcience <hi>excuſeth</hi> it ſelf again thus: Chriſt hath not only <hi>taken</hi> my <hi>debts</hi> and <hi>guilts</hi> upon <hi>him,</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:152194:45"/>but he hath <hi>endured</hi> the puniſhment, and <hi>paid</hi> the <hi>whole debt.</hi> Firſt, for my <hi>debts,</hi> I ſhall never contract <hi>greater</hi> or <hi>larger debts</hi> than he hath already <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged</hi> for me, and that <hi>before-hand</hi> too, and in <hi>better coyn</hi> than ever could have been pay'd by any other; <hi>not with ſilver and gold,</hi> but with that which is much more precious, <hi>his own heart-blood,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18.19.</p>
               <p>And for <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> hath he not undergone <hi>that</hi> alſo? And <hi>for whom</hi> did he undergo it, if not <hi>for me,</hi> and ſuch as I am? He had no ſin of his <hi>own</hi> to ſuffer for; no ſin by <hi>inheſion,</hi> his holy heart had not the <hi>leaſt defilement</hi> in it. Well then, it was for <hi>my ſins</hi> that he ſuffered: And did he not ſuffer to the <hi>full?</hi> Pray ſpeak Juſtice: Was <hi>one laſh forborn? One wound abated?</hi> Was he not all over <hi>wounded</hi> for my tranſgreſſions, even all in <hi>a gore-blood?</hi> How did the <hi>drops run trickling</hi> from him, while the <hi>ſtripes</hi> were laid <hi>thick</hi> on him? And why ſo, ſaies Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:152194:46"/>but that <hi>I might be healed?</hi> (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.5.) Hath not the <hi>Holy Ghoſt it ſelf</hi> taught me to ſay ſo, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded me to believe it: Now then what can <hi>Juſtice it ſelf deſire</hi> more? Ought any debt to be <hi>payed</hi> any more than <hi>once!</hi> or doth any <hi>just Law</hi> inflict <hi>puniſhment</hi> more than <hi>once,</hi> for <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame</hi> offence?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conſcience proceeds yet farther in its <hi>own defence,</hi> and adds <hi>one plea</hi> more, and 'tis a <hi>great one,</hi> without which the two former could never be <hi>verifyed</hi> by him, as to his <hi>own</hi> particular: What is that you'l ſay? Why, 'tis the <hi>blood of ſprinkling;</hi> for ſaies Conſcience, that it may indeed appear, that <hi>I am one</hi> of thoſe for whom Chriſt hath <hi>done this,</hi> for whoſe <hi>ſins</hi> he hath <hi>undergone</hi> his <hi>ſufferings,</hi> and whoſe <hi>debts</hi> he hath <hi>paid;</hi> that I am indeed one of his <hi>ſaved</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed</hi> ones: Behold here the <hi>ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings</hi> of his <hi>blood</hi> upon me. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever that is found the Conſcience can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:152194:46"/>not be evil, the <hi>heart is waſhed thorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> (<hi>Heb</hi> 10.22. But this <hi>(thorough-Grace</hi>) you cannot deny to be upon me, and therefore, while I adore the Mercy that hath <hi>thus ſprinkled</hi> mee, I <hi>fear not you Juſtice,</hi> nor any <hi>Challenge</hi> that you <hi>do,</hi> or <hi>can</hi> make againſt me.</p>
               <p>But then <hi>Satan,</hi> happily will come in, with his <hi>Accuſations,</hi> and theſe <hi>great</hi> and <hi>heavy.</hi> For that <hi>malicious foul-Fiend</hi> is wont to lay his charge <hi>deep (calumniari fortiter)</hi> and to the very <hi>beſt</hi> of Saints too in their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. Thus he did to <hi>Job,</hi> to <hi>Paul,</hi> yea, unto <hi>Chriſt himſelf;</hi> he wants not <hi>impudence,</hi> as we may ſee in <hi>Jobs</hi> caſe, nor cares he how many <hi>lyes</hi> hee tells, to <hi>traduce</hi> God, and <hi>trouble</hi> a Saint, and he never doth it more than when <hi>ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> or any other <hi>troubles</hi> ſeizeth him, and <hi>death</hi> approacheth. And the <hi>whole charge</hi> which he bringeth in uſually, is <hi>three-fold,</hi> or may all be reduced to <hi>three</hi> general heads.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:152194:47"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> Sins of <hi>Commiſsion,</hi> theſe he <hi>enumerates, multiplies,</hi> and <hi>aggravates</hi> with all manner of <hi>horrid</hi> circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, of <hi>time, place, manner, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> endeavours to make them all no leſs than <hi>preſumptuous</hi> ſins; ſins, <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Conſcience, againſt much light, great love, many obligations</hi> from the God of all Grace and Mercy. For the circumſtances of <hi>time,</hi> and <hi>place;</hi> don't you remember, ſaies this <hi>Accuſer of the Brethren,</hi> when and where you have been about your <hi>pretended</hi> holy Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, what <hi>wandrings</hi> of your eyes there were (by which one might <hi>gueſſe</hi> at the <hi>wandrings</hi> of your heart) how <hi>incompoſed</hi> you were, how <hi>ſoon</hi> wearied and tyred out, <hi>ſooner by farre,</hi> than when at your <hi>vain ſports</hi> or <hi>recreations?</hi> and don't you remember, how at <hi>ſuch a time,</hi> and in <hi>ſuch a place,</hi> you <hi>ſlept</hi> away the Sermon, how <hi>drowſie</hi> you were in Prayer; and the like again, at <hi>ſuch a time,</hi> and in <hi>ſuch a place,</hi> and ſo <hi>loſt</hi> your <hi>precious ſeaſon</hi> of grace, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:152194:47"/>the benefit of it, which at that time you might have enjoyed? Don't you <hi>remember</hi> theſe things? If you don't, I do: And then he proceeds to <hi>ſins</hi> of <hi>another kinde,</hi> and of <hi>another,</hi> and of <hi>another</hi> after them, and ſo comes <hi>pouring</hi> in with a <hi>great</hi> and <hi>long Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue</hi> of ſins of <hi>Commiſsion,</hi> with their <hi>aggravations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then <hi>Secondly,</hi> He brings in a <hi>new Charge,</hi> (as great and heavy as the former) of ſins of <hi>Omiſsion</hi> and <hi>neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects</hi> of Duty; neglects of <hi>ſecret Duties, Family-Duties,</hi> all ſorts of <hi>relative-Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> and aggravates them alſo by their Circumſtances. And</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Hereupon, what doth he inferre, but that <hi>all the Profeſsion</hi> which hath been made, hath been but a <hi>meere pretence</hi> to holineſs; but <hi>meere Hypocriſie,</hi> which he labours yet more <hi>ſtrongly</hi> to prove, by carrying his Charge <hi>farther:</hi> for ſaith he to the <hi>ſoul</hi> that he is <hi>now accuſing;</hi> is not all that is done by you, from <hi>ſuch</hi> and <hi>ſuch rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:152194:48"/>grounds; for ſuch and ſuch <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy ends?</hi> that you may <hi>get a name</hi> in the world? or make ſuch or ſuch <hi>carnal advantages</hi> to your ſelf? not out of any <hi>pure love</hi> at all, either to <hi>God,</hi> or the <hi>Duties;</hi> that you would be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to be <hi>ſincere</hi> in: And what is all this, but a kinde of <hi>holy-cheat,</hi> and a <hi>grand Imposture,</hi> both to your <hi>ſelf</hi> and <hi>others?</hi> and conſequently, will not the <hi>hopes</hi> and <hi>confidences</hi> you <hi>build</hi> upon theſe <hi>falſe</hi> foundations <hi>deceive</hi> you? And as for that <hi>repentance</hi> which you think to fly to for your <hi>refuge,</hi> whilſt you would make your ſelf and others believe, that you thereby <hi>get off</hi> from your guilts, and <hi>heal all</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. Alas! Is not that a <hi>meere cheat</hi> too, and a <hi>miſerable deceit</hi> of your own heart? For if there were a <hi>true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> in you, ſuch as you <hi>pretend</hi> to, would you fall into the <hi>ſame ſins</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and again, and that <hi>often?</hi> True Repentance, even <hi>you your ſelf</hi> know, is alwaies accompanied with an <hi>effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:152194:48"/>Reformation</hi> and a <hi>total breaking</hi> off from <hi>every</hi> evil. Now lay all this together, and <hi>are</hi> you, or <hi>can</hi> you, be the <hi>man,</hi> or the <hi>woman,</hi> you would have the world take you to be? No verily, it cannot be, your own <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> being Judge, as well as I: Thus you ſee what the <hi>Charge</hi> is, and how <hi>heavy,</hi> that Satan brings in: <hi>to all which an excuſing Conſcience, makes anſwer, and defends it ſelf thus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> For thoſe ſins, ſaies Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that you like a <hi>Devil</hi> accuſe me with, when the matter is <hi>well-look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> into, will they not (at leaſt, <hi>very many</hi> of them) prove <hi>more yours,</hi> than mine? eſpecially <hi>ſuch</hi> as you call <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous</hi> ſins, and aggravate with ſuch <hi>grievous circumſtances,</hi> 'twas <hi>you</hi> that <hi>tempted</hi> me to them, that <hi>hurried</hi> me on to the committing of them, was it not? 'Tis <hi>you</hi> that laid the <hi>objects</hi> before me, by which I was <hi>enticed;</hi> that <hi>ſtirred</hi> up <hi>the old corruption,</hi> which at firſt <hi>you foisted into my nature,</hi> and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:152194:49"/>which you have ever ſince <hi>fomented,</hi> and brought <hi>fuel</hi> to. This is <hi>one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe</hi> that Conſcience makes. But</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſcience adds. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny not, but though you as a <hi>ſoul-mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer,</hi> moſt <hi>maliciouſly tempted</hi> me, yet ſince I <hi>conſented</hi> the ſins were <hi>mine,</hi> as well as <hi>yours,</hi> both the ſins of <hi>Omiſsion,</hi> and the ſins of <hi>commiſsion;</hi> but <hi>three things</hi> I can ſay for my ſelf, that <hi>you can never ſay.</hi> (1.) I have a moſt <hi>gracious Saviour,</hi> and <hi>Redeemer,</hi> that is <hi>given</hi> to me, and that hath <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken</hi> for me: Can you ſay this <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil?</hi> you know you cannot; <hi>He took not upon him the nature of Angels, but the ſeed of</hi> Abraham, <hi>even of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> Abraham, whoſe ſeed I am. (2.) I have <hi>two</hi> natures in me, a <hi>new Nature,</hi> not the <hi>old</hi> onely; I am a <hi>new</hi> man, a Son of the <hi>ſecond Adam,</hi> as well as of the <hi>firſt:</hi> I am <hi>regenerate</hi> and (tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Grace) am <hi>born again;</hi> I have ſomething of <hi>Heaven</hi> in me, but <hi>you are all Devil, all Hell.</hi> (3.) I can
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:152194:49"/>truely ſay, what-ever you ſay to the <hi>contrary,</hi> that I have <hi>ſincerely repented,</hi> and do repent <hi>daily,</hi> which you can never do. For you are <hi>given up to a damned ſtate,</hi> ſealed to deſtruction, and <hi>reſerved for the day of wrath.</hi> As for my <hi>Repentance,</hi> which you object <hi>ſo much</hi> againſt, and by <hi>all your might</hi> do labour to invalidate; and my <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion</hi> too, which you ſo <hi>falſly</hi> aſperſe, as if it were <hi>meer hypocriſie:</hi> I can e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence the <hi>truth of both</hi> of them thus: (1.) <hi>I hate the ſin which I do, and the evil which I do, I would not do,</hi> my <hi>will</hi> is againſt it; and the <hi>good that I would do,</hi> 'tis true, <hi>I do it not,</hi> becauſe <hi>ſin is preſent with me,</hi> but my <hi>will</hi> is to do it, notwithſtanding; and in <hi>Gods ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count,</hi> 'tis the <hi>Will</hi> that denominates the man, as the <hi>will</hi> is, ſuch the man is 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.11, 12. (2.) Whereas you charge me with falling into the <hi>ſame</hi> ſins <hi>again,</hi> and <hi>again,</hi> I confeſs it, whilſt I carry a <hi>body of death</hi> about me, and a <hi>Law in my members warring
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:152194:50"/>againſt the Law of my minde,</hi> and both theſe <hi>agitated</hi> by <hi>ſuch a tempting Devil</hi> as thou art; I do fall <hi>daily.</hi> Sins of <hi>day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incurſion</hi> and <hi>infirmity</hi> come in upon me: But haſt thou not heard <hi>Devil,</hi> that <hi>the Righteous man falleth ſeven times,</hi> (that is often) <hi>and riſeth again, Prov.</hi> 24.16. For repentance is not onely <hi>one ſingle act,</hi> but 'tis an <hi>habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual grace</hi> in the heart, proceeding from the <hi>new Creature</hi> formed there, whoſe <hi>proper act</hi> it is. All <hi>diſtinct</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures act according to their kinde; and act <hi>neceſſarily;</hi> the Sun <hi>ſhines,</hi> and <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſhines,</hi> becauſe it <hi>ſhines naturally,</hi> and can do no other; <hi>So doth grace,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies act like it ſelf, and cannot <hi>ceaſe</hi> acting. But yet, (3.) Conſcience <hi>far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> excuſeth it ſelf, and tells the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> to his face, that as he would accuſe it of <hi>more evil</hi> than 'tis guilty of, ſo he hath <hi>more good</hi> in him than the <hi>Devil knows</hi> of, for <hi>what-ever</hi> Grace, <hi>what-e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> good thoughts or affections are in the <hi>heart,</hi> the Devil <hi>knows nothing</hi> of all
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:152194:50"/>that, the <hi>heart</hi> and the <hi>workings</hi> of it, being altogether a <hi>ſecret</hi> unto him, ſo that how <hi>many</hi> an <hi>holy ſtruggle</hi> may be in the <hi>heart,</hi> againſt <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that</hi> ſin, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that</hi> temptation; How <hi>many</hi> a <hi>ſharpe fight</hi> and <hi>combate</hi> there, the Devil is <hi>ignorant</hi> of: Though he <hi>ſee</hi> the <hi>tears</hi> that drop, and <hi>hear</hi> the <hi>ſighs</hi> and <hi>groans</hi> that the <hi>afflicted</hi> and <hi>grieved</hi> ſoul utters for ſin, yet hee <hi>knows not</hi> what 'tis for, unleſs it bee made known to him in ſo many <hi>articu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated words.</hi> Now then how many <hi>thouſand</hi> holy ſighs and groans; how <hi>many</hi> repentings may there be; how <hi>many</hi> ardent <hi>affections,</hi> and pious <hi>ejacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations</hi> may paſs from the <hi>heart</hi> to <hi>Heaven,</hi> which the <hi>Devil may not know the reaſon of,</hi> and of which alone, <hi>God</hi> is witneſs? This then is <hi>another excuſe</hi> that Conſcience makes for it ſelf, and 'tis <hi>none of the leaſt.</hi> And yet, (4.) There is <hi>one</hi> more, a <hi>very good</hi> one, when all elſe is ſaid that can be, the Conſcience <hi>flies</hi> to that, in 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:152194:51"/>
                  <hi>The blood of Christ cleanſeth me from all ſin.</hi> So that let the Devil accuſe as <hi>home,</hi> and charge as <hi>deep</hi> as hee can, yet <hi>here,</hi> to be ſure, is a <hi>full anſwer</hi> for him, an <hi>irrefragable one,</hi> and ſuch as he can <hi>never invalidate,</hi> or take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the <hi>force</hi> of.</p>
               <p>And in caſe Satan ſhould be ſo <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent</hi> as to <hi>urge</hi> the matter <hi>farther,</hi> and ſay, that is true, <hi>the blood of Chriſt cleanſeth from all ſin,</hi> but that belongs to none but a <hi>true Beleiver,</hi> which you can <hi>never prove</hi> your ſelf to be.</p>
               <p>To this Conſcience anſwers like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and that <hi>roundly</hi> and <hi>ſmartly:</hi> Thou <hi>lyeſt</hi> Devil; and beſides thou art <hi>no Judge in this caſe,</hi> it comes not within thy <hi>cogniſance;</hi> what <hi>tranſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> are in my ſoul, what <hi>mutual em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces,</hi> betwixt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>me;</hi> what <hi>acts</hi> of <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>love</hi> are in <hi>that ſecret place;</hi> as I ſaid before, thou knoweſt not: It doth not therefore follow, it is not; <hi>de non entibus &amp; de non appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentibus idem eſt judicium;</hi> things that
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:152194:51"/>appear not, to one that is ignorant, are as if they were not; Let <hi>that matter</hi> alone <hi>Devil,</hi> for as cunning as thou art, thou art <hi>no Judge</hi> in it; it is <hi>enough</hi> that <hi>my God,</hi> who alone is (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>the knower of the heart,</hi> Acts 15.8. <hi>knows that I love him,</hi> and <hi>believe</hi> in him, whether thou knoweſt it, or not.</p>
               <p>Thus now we ſee what a <hi>good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> is, in both the parts of it; both (as 'tis <hi>honeſtè bona, &amp; pacatè bona</hi>) as 'tis a <hi>quiet</hi> Conſcience, and an <hi>excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> Conſcience, <hi>every way</hi> void of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, <hi>both towards God, and towards men;</hi> and where ſuch a Conſcience is; is it not a <hi>ſufficient fortification</hi> againſt the fear of Death? What is it that can be a <hi>juſt ground</hi> of trouble to <hi>this</hi> man? That which is the <hi>moſt diſquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> thing of all, namely, his <hi>ſin,</hi> and the <hi>guilt</hi> of it, that is <hi>removed;</hi> Chriſt hath taken it <hi>off</hi> from him; What is it can be matter of <hi>terrour</hi> to him, at the <hi>great Tribunal,</hi> which he muſt one
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:152194:52"/>day ſtand before? <hi>No enemy will appear againſt him there,</hi> for God is <hi>reconciled</hi> to him; and hee that ſhall ſit there as <hi>his Judge,</hi> is no other than <hi>his Redeemer.</hi> And if Conſcience here, even in this life <hi>(whoſe internal motions are known to none but God himſelf, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which ground none elſe but he can im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Law upon it, and oblige it)</hi> be at ſo much eaſe. Surely 'tis from the <hi>ſame God</hi> that he is going to, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone can <hi>comfort,</hi> or <hi>afflict</hi> the perſon to all eternity hereafter, whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience he alone alſo can <hi>comfort</hi> or <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict</hi> in time.</p>
               <p>But I haſten to anſwer <hi>two imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant</hi> objections, which ſeem much to contradict all that hath been ſaid hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:152194:52"/>
               <head>SECT. 9.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Two important objections anſwered, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the preceeding doctrine, and what hath been ſaid upon it.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>FIrſt,</hi> It may be, ſome will ſay, ſhall we think that all thoſe that are <hi>afraid,</hi> or <hi>unwilling</hi> to dye, are to be looked upon as perſons <hi>without</hi> ſuch a <hi>quiet,</hi> and <hi>excuſing</hi> Conſcience or, as thoſe which have not ſuch <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward teſtimonies</hi> of a good eſtate, and that in all the particulars, which have been mentioned? Would not this be <hi>very uncharitable</hi> to paſs ſuch a cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? Yea, and very <hi>unwarrantable</hi> too, and againſt plain evidence both of <hi>Scripture</hi> and <hi>Experience?</hi> Of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, which poſitively affirms (<hi>Heb.</hi> 2.15.) that <hi>ſome</hi> (and thoſe precious ones too, for 'tis ſpoken of Saints) <hi>through fear of death are all their life time ſubject to bondage.</hi> And doth not
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:152194:53"/>experience farther <hi>prove</hi> it, almoſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day? How many <hi>choice Servants</hi> of Chriſt, have met with <hi>hard ſtruggles</hi> when they come to dye? Have been willing to live <hi>yet longer,</hi> if it might bee? Have they not had their <hi>dreads</hi> on them? Yea, their (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>pangs</hi> and <hi>bands in their death,</hi> like a woman in travel?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> On the <hi>other hand,</hi> is it not a very <hi>ordinary</hi> thing to ſee <hi>wicked men</hi> live and dye in peace? Men as <hi>vile,</hi> as <hi>prophane</hi> and <hi>deboiſhed</hi> as any the earth hath, and yet <hi>their Conſciences are quiet</hi> notwithſtanding; they have no <hi>diſturbance</hi> at all from them: nor as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaies, have they any <hi>bands in their death,</hi> (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.4.) but ſeem to paſs out of the world, as <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> as <hi>Lambs,</hi> and without any <hi>fear</hi> at all upon them.</p>
               <p>Theſe are two <hi>conſiderable Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> indeed, and muſt be anſwered, and to <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> too, leaſt the truth before delivered, bee <hi>prejudiced</hi> and <hi>ſhaken</hi> by it.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:152194:53"/>
               <p> I anſwer therefore to <hi>both</hi> in order, and firſt to the firſt objection, I ſay three things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> by way of <hi>conceſsion,</hi> I grant it, that many who have indeed ſuch a <hi>quiet</hi> and <hi>excuſing</hi> Conſcience, a Conſcience <hi>void of offence both towards God, and towards men,</hi> as I have been ſpeaking of, do <hi>notwithſtanding</hi> dye with fears upon them, and ſeem to be taken out of the world by <hi>violence,</hi> rather than <hi>freely to go out of it,</hi> and this contrary to the very precepts, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of an <hi>Heathen moraliſt.</hi> For what ſaies <hi>Seneca</hi> in his 104th Epiſtle, <hi>Vir fortis &amp; ſapiens exire debet è vita, non trahi;</hi> a wiſe and a valiant man, ought to go readily out of this life, not to be drawn. And again, <hi>quid eſt obſecro, cur timeat mortem homo?</hi> What is there in death (conſidered ſimply in it ſelf) that a man ſhould fear? <hi>cum illâ nihil ſit mali, niſi quod ante ipſam est, timeri;</hi> the greateſt evil of it, is to be afraid of it, before it comes?
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:152194:54"/>
                  <hi>Thus he, even a very Heathen:</hi> Well, but yet for all that, ſuch is the <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary timidity</hi> of ſome perſons, and good ones too, ſuch is their <hi>aptneſs</hi> to <hi>deſpond,</hi> partly from the <hi>natural conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> and <hi>temper</hi> of their <hi>melancholy</hi> bodies and mindes; partly from the <hi>moleſtation</hi> of the great enemy of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde <hi>(through Divine permiſsion)</hi> the <hi>Devil,</hi> that the work of <hi>natures diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution,</hi> comes off <hi>hard</hi> with them, and is a <hi>much more difficult</hi> task to them, than to ſome others: And the truth is, <hi>who,</hi> that is a <hi>Son</hi> or <hi>Daughter</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> let them be never ſo <hi>holy,</hi> and never ſo <hi>fit</hi> for Heaven, but more or leſs, have ſomething of a <hi>cohorreſcency</hi> of death upon them? Two ſuch <hi>old friends,</hi> and ſo <hi>intimate</hi> as the <hi>body</hi> and the <hi>ſoul,</hi> are <hi>loath</hi> to part; It is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural for every thing to <hi>deſire</hi> and <hi>ſeek</hi> the <hi>preſervation</hi> of it ſelf, and to <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe</hi> and be <hi>afraid</hi> of that which <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys</hi> it. Hence 'tis that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in the third Book of his <hi>Ethicks,</hi> the fixth
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:152194:54"/>
                  <hi>Chapter,</hi> tells us that (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>Death is moſt dreadful.</hi> Thus alſo <hi>another Heathen</hi> (Epicur. <hi>Ad me nunc. Apud Laert.</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>of all evils, death is the moſt formidable:</hi> But what need we go to <hi>Heathen</hi> Authours for this, ſince the <hi>Scripture</hi> it ſelf affirms it, whilſt it ſaith of Death, <hi>that 'tis the King of terrours? Job</hi> 18.14. But</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> I anſwer, That though theſe <hi>fears</hi> are found <hi>ſtirring</hi> and <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbing</hi> the mindes, even of <hi>good men and women,</hi> as well as others; and we have <hi>often experience</hi> of it, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny it; yet this I affirm, that the perſons qualified as aforeſaid, with a <hi>good</hi> and a <hi>quiet</hi> Conſcience, have <hi>no juſt reaſon</hi> to be ſo <hi>fearful,</hi> but have <hi>good</hi> and <hi>ſufficient</hi> ground to the contrary. What mens fears are <hi>(de facto)</hi> is <hi>one</hi> thing, and the <hi>ground</hi> of them is <hi>another:</hi> that good men have <hi>no juſt ground,</hi> no <hi>reaſon</hi> to bee <hi>thus affrighted,</hi> I ſtill contend; for
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:152194:55"/>why ſhould they, ſince <hi>God is recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled</hi> to them, as hath been ſaid; and ſince they have <hi>ſuch a Mediatour</hi> and <hi>Advocate</hi> in the Heavens, as <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and ſince they have their <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> in their own <hi>boſomes,</hi> and clear evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of their own <hi>regenerated</hi> and <hi>ſanctified</hi> ſtate, and of their being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready received into <hi>favour</hi> with <hi>that God,</hi> that they are going to? And therefore,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is <hi>very rare</hi> that any <hi>Childe</hi> of God <hi>dies</hi> under <hi>theſe fears,</hi> but <hi>ſooner</hi> or <hi>latter,</hi> they make a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt</hi> over them, at leaſt, in ſome <hi>good</hi> degree; <hi>buffetings</hi> they ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times have, and may have, for <hi>ſome time,</hi> and 'tis ſeldome that the <hi>moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent</hi> of the Saints eſcape them (<hi>Heman's</hi> caſe may be many a <hi>good mans</hi> beſides, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88. throughout) but when do we hear of any of them that dye <hi>deſpairing,</hi> and go out of the world with <hi>theſe terrours unvanquiſhed?</hi> I would be <hi>tender</hi> in the caſe, and not
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:152194:55"/>be <hi>poſitive</hi> in determining, <hi>one way,</hi> or <hi>other,</hi> for <hi>Francis Spira</hi>'s ſake: But am <hi>moſt inclined</hi> to think, that who-ever are delivered <hi>from the wrath to come,</hi> are alſo delivered from the <hi>prevailing fear</hi> of it, before they breathe out their <hi>laſt breath.</hi> Many and famous are the <hi>inſtances,</hi> which wee have of this kinde; ſuch as Miſtreſs <hi>Honywood,</hi> Mr. <hi>Throgmorton,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Holland,</hi> Mris. <hi>Katherine Brett,</hi> and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which are recorded by ſuch as have left their <hi>Funeral Diſcourſes</hi> in Print, and have written the <hi>lives</hi> of <hi>holy men</hi> and <hi>Women;</hi> Thoſe that liſt may finde ſome of them in the works of Dr. <hi>Thomas Taylor,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bolton,</hi> Mr. <hi>Gataker,</hi> Mr. <hi>Samuel Clark,</hi> and elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>other Objection,</hi> I likewiſe anſwer. Suppoſe a prophane <hi>Senſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt,</hi> a <hi>Drunkard,</hi> a <hi>Whoremonger,</hi> a <hi>bruitiſh Rioter,</hi> that waſtes his <hi>body,</hi> his <hi>eſtate,</hi> his <hi>time,</hi> his <hi>conſcience,</hi> in the purſuit of his <hi>beaſtly</hi> and <hi>ſilthy luſts;</hi>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:152194:56"/>that <hi>revels</hi> it out, <hi>night</hi> and <hi>day,</hi> without <hi>any the leaſt regard</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>ownſoul:</hi> Suppoſe a <hi>covetous earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly muck-worme,</hi> that <hi>grip's</hi> and <hi>graſp's (per fas, &amp; nefas) right,</hi> or <hi>wrong,</hi> hee cares not how, ſo he get an <hi>eſtate,</hi> fill his <hi>coffers</hi> with ſilver, and his <hi>heart</hi> with guilt, by <hi>fraud, deceit,</hi> and <hi>oppreſsion,</hi> that <hi>ſqueezeeth</hi> the <hi>Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs</hi> and the <hi>Widdow,</hi> the <hi>poor</hi> and <hi>needy;</hi> that <hi>over-reacheth</hi> his innocent and well-meaning Neighbour. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the <hi>proud</hi> and <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> perſon, that <hi>over-looks,</hi> and <hi>ſcorns</hi> every one below himſelf; yea, thoſe that are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way his <hi>equals</hi> at leaſt, if not <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than he;</hi> the <hi>high</hi> and <hi>lofty</hi> perſon that can debauch himſelf <hi>without any ſcruple,</hi> and renounce all <hi>former prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,</hi> and <hi>practices;</hi> that can <hi>ſwear,</hi> and <hi>for-ſwear;</hi> do any thing be it <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo vile,</hi> and <hi>impious,</hi> ſo that hee may <hi>riſe</hi> by it, grow <hi>higher</hi> in place and <hi>eſteem</hi> among men, and attain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch a <hi>grandeur,</hi> and <hi>greatneſs</hi> that
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:152194:56"/>hee hath propounded unto himſelf. Suppoſe a <hi>malicious envious</hi> perſon, (and therein as like the <hi>Devil</hi> as any you can meet with) a <hi>bloody minded</hi> man, that <hi>hates</hi> God, and all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that <hi>perſecutes</hi> a Saint with great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>rage</hi> and <hi>fury,</hi> for no <hi>other</hi> reaſon but becauſe he <hi>loves</hi> God, <hi>owns</hi> his <hi>Waies, Ordinances,</hi> and <hi>Inſtitutions;</hi> Walks holily, and by the <hi>ſhining</hi> light, of his converſation, <hi>condemns</hi> the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of the wicked. Suppoſe an <hi>Athieſt,</hi> an <hi>Apoſtate,</hi> that hath <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lived</hi> all Conſcience; that bids defy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to that <hi>holy profeſsion</hi> which once he ſeemed to make to <hi>God,</hi> and every thing that hath his <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription</hi> upon it. Once more, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe an <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> not only a <hi>groſs</hi> but a <hi>fine-ſpun</hi> Hypocrite (of which there are too many in theſe daies) that make <hi>great pretenſrons</hi> to Religion it ſelf, that ſeems as <hi>devout,</hi> as <hi>zealous,</hi> and as much <hi>concerned</hi> for God and his Truth, for his <hi>holy</hi> Waies and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:152194:57"/>as thoſe that are <hi>moſt ſincere;</hi> but all this, not in <hi>pure love,</hi> to thoſe things, but for ſome <hi>worldly,</hi> or <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> ends, which otherwiſe he cannot accompliſh. I ſay, ſuppoſe that <hi>theſe</hi> and <hi>many ſuch like,</hi> as guilty of other evils, as great as any that I have <hi>now</hi> mentioned, ſhould after their whole life <hi>thus ſpent,</hi> and that <hi>impenitently,</hi> dye in peace without any the <hi>leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe</hi> or <hi>check</hi> of Conſcience, would you <hi>ſay,</hi> or can you <hi>think,</hi> that theſe men have a <hi>good,</hi> and <hi>truely quiet</hi> Conſcience? Men <hi>thus obdurated,</hi> and given up (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) to an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicious</hi> and <hi>reprobated minde,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>'s phraſe is, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.28. Men of ſo <hi>profligated</hi> a life, and ſo <hi>prodigiouſly</hi> wicked, that <hi>after the hardneſs of their heart, and that cannot repent, have treaſured up to themſelves wrath againſt the day of Wrath.</hi> I ſay, is there, or can there be any ground to imagine that they have a <hi>good</hi> and a <hi>quiet</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? What, becauſe they live,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:152194:57"/>and dye thus, like an <hi>Hog</hi> in his ſtie, that dyes of the <hi>Meaſles,</hi> or the <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine,</hi> (or ſome other ſuch <hi>Plague</hi> that a <hi>beaſt</hi> is ſubject to) with ſcarſe a <hi>grunt</hi> or a <hi>groan,</hi> is all well therefore with him? Alas! is there not a great deal more cauſe to ſay, and that <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any breach of charity,</hi> that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of ſuch as theſe, is <hi>at beſt,</hi> but a <hi>ſleepy Conſcience,</hi> a Conſcience lull'd into a <hi>damnable ſecurity,</hi> and <hi>inſenſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> a <hi>ſeared</hi> Conſcience, a Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <hi>paſt feeling?</hi> Than which, what can be a <hi>greater Judgement,</hi> or <hi>ſorer Doom?</hi> When God ſaies of any man, (as in <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.11.) <hi>He that is filthy, let him be filthy ſtill;</hi> Let the Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer, the Blaſphemer, the Idolater, be an Adulterer <hi>ſtill,</hi> a Blaſphemer <hi>ſtill,</hi> an Idolater <hi>ſtill;</hi> When he ſhall ſay as he did to <hi>Ephraim</hi> (<hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.17.) <hi>Ephraim</hi> is an Apoſtate, <hi>he is joyned to Idols, let him alone;</hi> Let him <hi>live</hi> and <hi>dye</hi> in his ſin without repentance; Let him <hi>periſh</hi> and go down to <hi>Hell;</hi>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:152194:58"/>and let him go <hi>without all ſenſe,</hi> or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of his <hi>danger,</hi> with a <hi>blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> minde, and an <hi>hardened</hi> heart; Let him fall into his <hi>own deſtruction,</hi> and that without recovery, when he is <hi>leaſt aware</hi> of it. Can any thing bee <hi>more terrible</hi> than this? And yet what leſs than this can they look for, who live and dye <hi>in a ſtate of unregeneracy,</hi> let their paſſage out of this world ſeem never ſo <hi>peaceable</hi> and <hi>quiet?</hi> For though they have <hi>no bands in their death,</hi> as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> himſelf confeſſeth (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.4.) Yet being <hi>wicked men</hi> and <hi>women,</hi> they are <hi>far</hi> from a <hi>truely good</hi> and <hi>quiet</hi> Coſcience. And ſo now I think I have anſwered <hi>this obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> too, and that without leaving any <hi>room for a Reply.</hi> I come next to the <hi>uſe</hi> of all which is two-fold.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:152194:58"/>
               <head>SECT. 10.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The uſes and improvement of the point. Firſt by way of information, and then of exhortation, both to good and bad.</p>
               </argument>
               <div type="information">
                  <head>By way of Information.</head>
                  <p>SEe here the <hi>difference</hi> the <hi>vaſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference,</hi> between men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <hi>regenerate</hi> and <hi>unregenerate;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween men <hi>reconciled</hi> to God and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconciled;</hi> between men of a <hi>good</hi> Conſcience, and an <hi>evil</hi> Conſcience; and that both in their <hi>life,</hi> and in their <hi>death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In their <hi>life,</hi> which in many things differs <hi>very much,</hi> I will reduce all to four heads, briefly. (1.) One of them, the regenerate perſon, lives <hi>holily,</hi> the whole courſe of his life is <hi>holy,</hi> in all the <hi>deſigns</hi> of it, in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual <hi>practiſe,</hi> in a <hi>ſincere, thorough, univerſal, conſtant</hi> obedience. He is freed from the <hi>bondage</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:152194:59"/>ſin; he is no way <hi>under the dominion of it;</hi> it doth not <hi>reign in his mortal body;</hi> but he is very much <hi>dead unto ſin, and alive unto God.</hi> There's no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the world that he <hi>hates</hi> and <hi>flys</hi> from, <hi>ſo much</hi> as ſin and all <hi>occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> and <hi>temptations,</hi> leading to it; Hee'l as ſoon adventure himſelf into a <hi>neſt of hiſsing Serpents,</hi> or into an houſe <hi>infected with the Plague,</hi> as to go into any <hi>place</hi> or <hi>company,</hi> where his heart may be <hi>endangered,</hi> or his eyes and ears be <hi>vitiated,</hi> with <hi>corrupt,</hi> and <hi>corrupting</hi> objects, <hi>diſcourſes</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples:</hi> And as for the <hi>Devil</hi> that is alwaies injecting <hi>filthineſs</hi> into his thoughts, or laying <hi>ſnares</hi> before him, and ſtill ſome way or other, is <hi>ſolicit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> him to evil, he is ſo much <hi>aware</hi> of him, that he <hi>ſtands upon his guard</hi> continually; is evermore <hi>ſtruggling</hi> with him, and by his <hi>holy combates</hi> with him, (through the ſtrength of Chriſt) never fails of making <hi>ſome conqueſt</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him, <hi>more or leſſe</hi> and whilſt he
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:152194:59"/>
                     <hi>reſiſts</hi> him, cauſeth him to <hi>fly</hi> from him: But now the other, the <hi>unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate perſon,</hi> how <hi>wickedly</hi> and <hi>wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly,</hi> doth he live? What an <hi>unholy</hi> and <hi>impure</hi> life? How doth he <hi>wallow in his filthineſe,</hi> as a Swine in its mire; and <hi>lick it up,</hi> as a Dog doth his vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit? how doth his heart lye <hi>aſoak</hi> in ſin? and what a <hi>miſerable Vaſſal</hi> and <hi>Slave</hi> is he to it? <hi>(multos Dominos ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, qui unum non habet)</hi> How many Lords is he under, whileſt he diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beys the Lord his Maker? every luſt exerciſeth a <hi>domination</hi> over him, a <hi>great,</hi> and a <hi>ſevere Tyranny.</hi> How is he <hi>diſtracted</hi> betwixt <hi>this</hi> ſin and <hi>that,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>this</hi> temptation and <hi>that?</hi> And how <hi>buſie</hi> is he to make-<hi>proviſion</hi> for every Luſt? I, and he muſt pleaſe the <hi>Devil</hi> too, whoſe <hi>Vaſſal</hi> he like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe is, ſo far is he from <hi>reſiſting</hi> or <hi>oppoſing</hi> him; and indeed how can he, he having laid his <hi>chains</hi> upon him? For doth it not fare with the <hi>Devils Bond-Slaves,</hi> whom he <hi>holds Captives
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:152194:60"/>at his will,</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26. as it doth with the <hi>Turkiſh Galley-Slaves,</hi> who being both <hi>Manacled, Shackled,</hi> and <hi>faſtned</hi> to their Seats and Oares, are made to work till the <hi>Irons eat into their very fleſh,</hi> and beſides that, to ſuffer as many <hi>cruel blows</hi> as their <hi>ſavage Task<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters</hi> have a minde to give them: This then is one difference. A ſecond is this, The Regenerate perſon <hi>walks with God,</hi> is in <hi>amity</hi> and <hi>friendſhip;</hi> with him, as <hi>Enoch</hi> was; there is a <hi>great good</hi> will betwixt God and him; they are <hi>agreed together,</hi> as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets Phraſe is (<hi>Amos</hi> 3.3.) <hi>can two walk together except they be agreed?</hi> It is the regenerate man's <hi>daily</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> care, in all things to <hi>pleaſe God,</hi> to do his <hi>will,</hi> yea, <hi>all</hi> his <hi>will,</hi> this is <hi>meat and drink to him;</hi> he is never <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pleaſed,</hi> than when like Chriſt himſelf (<hi>Luke</hi> 2.49.) he is <hi>about his Fathers buſineſs;</hi> this he mindes <hi>more than his appointed food.</hi> (as <hi>Job.</hi> did,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:152194:60"/>
                     <hi>Job</hi> 23.12.) He will rather loſe a <hi>Meals meat;</hi> two or three (for fail) than an opportunity of doing a <hi>ſervice</hi> for God, or <hi>wherein</hi> he may any way injoy <hi>ſome good</hi> from him, in <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that</hi> Duty, or Ordinance: Which kindneſs God takes <hi>great notice</hi> of, and will be <hi>ſure</hi> to anſwer again to him, and ſome way or other makes him <hi>ſenſible,</hi> how <hi>well</hi> he takes it at his hands: <hi>This bleſsing,</hi> and <hi>that,</hi> ſhall ſpeak it out unto him; he will make good all that he hath <hi>promiſed to them that keep his Statutes, and his Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to do them, Deut.</hi> 28.1.-15. All manner of bleſſings ſhal come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him; <hi>the bleſsings of the City, and of the Field, of the Basket, and of the ſtore;</hi> yea, of <hi>Heaven</hi> and of <hi>Earth,</hi> as is there at large expreſſed. But now, as to the <hi>unregenerate</hi> perſon, it is <hi>quite</hi> otherwiſe with him, he is at <hi>enmity</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> with him; he walks <hi>contrary</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> to him; he <hi>hates God,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> hates him, as 'tis
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:152194:61"/>ſaid of the <hi>howling Shepherds,</hi> (ſo they are called, <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.3.) that had <hi>no pity</hi> upon the Lords people; (<hi>ver.</hi> 5.) <hi>their ſoul,</hi> ſaies God, <hi>abhored me, and my ſoul loathed them,</hi> (<hi>ver.</hi> 8.) <hi>the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and him that loveth violence his ſoul hates, Pſal.</hi> 11.5. And thereupon muſt not ſuch an one needs be <hi>under a curſe</hi> a <hi>diſmal</hi> one, and may he not <hi>reaſonably</hi> look for it, every <hi>day?</hi> Yea, every <hi>hour,</hi> every <hi>moment,</hi> hath he not cauſe to fear that one <hi>curſe</hi> or other; one <hi>ſore Judgement</hi> or another, will fall upon him? What ſaies <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> Pſal. 7.11, 12, 13. <hi>God is angry with the wicked every day, if he turn not, he will whet his Sword, hee hath bent his bow, and made it ready. Hee hath alſo prepared for him the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of death; he ordaineth his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows againſt the Perſecutors.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.6. <hi>Upon the wicked he ſhall rain ſnares, fire and brimſtone, and an horrible</hi> (in the Margent, 'tis a burning) <hi>tempeſt, this ſhall be the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Cup.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:152194:61"/>
                  <p> And this is a ſecond Difference, the third follows. A regenerate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hath an <hi>awakened</hi> an <hi>enlightned,</hi> a <hi>tender</hi> Conſcience, a <hi>good</hi> and <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt</hi> Conſcience, that will <hi>do all its Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices</hi> faithfully; It will <hi>inform, accuſe,</hi> give <hi>true evidence, rebuke,</hi> and paſſe a <hi>right Judgement</hi> too, as the caſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires. It will not ſuffer him to <hi>lye in his ſin,</hi> or to <hi>neglect</hi> the means that may <hi>remove,</hi> either the <hi>guilt</hi> or <hi>filth</hi> thereof, and 'tis his <hi>conſtant care</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to keep it <hi>wakeful</hi> and <hi>tender,</hi> apt to <hi>be convinced,</hi> and apt <hi>to rebuke</hi> upon all occaſions: He no way deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſeth the <hi>fore-warnings</hi> of it, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent ſin, and the <hi>checks</hi> of it, when ſin is <hi>working,</hi> and ready to put forth it ſelf, for by <hi>this means,</hi> principally the <hi>amity</hi> is <hi>kept up</hi> between God and him, and the <hi>peace</hi> that he injoyes inwardly, maintained. But how much <hi>otherwiſe</hi> is it with an <hi>unregenerate man?</hi> either he is a man of <hi>no Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> that is, makes no Conſcience
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:152194:62"/>of any thing he doth, <hi>ſcruples nothing doubts nothing,</hi> but adventures upon <hi>any</hi> thing, <hi>any</hi> breach of Gods <hi>holy,</hi> and <hi>righteous</hi> Law, any act that may ſatisfie his <hi>own evil heart,</hi> be it never ſo foul; either <hi>ſees no hurt,</hi> or <hi>will</hi> ſee none in it, is <hi>willingly ignorant,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, in another caſe, (2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.5.) and to that end, <hi>hates to be reformed,</hi> cannot endure a <hi>ſoul-ſearching</hi> Miniſtry, or a <hi>plain-deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Friend</hi> that may <hi>convince</hi> him of the <hi>ſinfulneſs</hi> of his heart and waies, and ſo lies <hi>drowzing</hi> under a <hi>ſleepy,</hi> and kinde of <hi>dead Conſcience;</hi> or elſe, if his Conſcience doth <hi>ſtir,</hi> at any time, and begin, either <hi>latrare,</hi> or <hi>lacerare,</hi> to <hi>barke,</hi> and it may be, to <hi>bite</hi> too; what doth he do preſently? Doth he not do by this his <hi>barking</hi> and <hi>biting</hi> Conſcience (ready to fly in his face) as a man that hath a <hi>fierce Maſtiff-Dog, tye</hi> him up or <hi>Muzzle</hi> him? Thus he deals with his Conſcience; and that he may bee the <hi>leſs at leiſure</hi> to
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:152194:62"/>hearken to, or hear the <hi>brawlings</hi> of it, is it not his <hi>common practiſe</hi> to go into ſome <hi>ſuch company,</hi> or engage in ſome <hi>ſuch buſineſs,</hi> or indulge himſelf in ſome <hi>ſuch pleaſure, recreation,</hi> or other <hi>ſinful</hi> divertizement, as may <hi>wholly take him off</hi> from giving any, the leaſt attendance, or regard to it? So long as he can keep his <hi>eyes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen,</hi> he is thus employed, and when <hi>night comes,</hi> what care doth he take either to <hi>ingorge,</hi> or <hi>intoxicate</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſo as he may <hi>ſleep it out,</hi> till day-light returns, or at leaſt, <hi>that hour</hi> of it, that gives him the advantage of his <hi>accuſtomed courſe</hi> of ſinning, with his wicked Companions, <hi>day after day?</hi> Thus he lives and <hi>waſtes</hi> his <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious</hi> time, not <hi>caring,</hi> or <hi>knowing,</hi> how <hi>ſoon</hi> death may <hi>Arreſt</hi> him, and <hi>ſpoil</hi> his ſport.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly</hi> and Laſtly, A <hi>regenerate</hi> perſon is a man <hi>Crucified to the World, and the World to him:</hi> He is no more moved, or affected, with the <hi>pleaſures,</hi>
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:152194:63"/>the <hi>delights,</hi> and <hi>lying vanities</hi> of this world, than a <hi>living man</hi> is pleaſed with the preſence of a <hi>dead Wife,</hi> lying by him; and all the <hi>ſplendours, gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deurs, blandiſhments, allurements,</hi> and <hi>bewitchments</hi> of this world, work <hi>no more</hi> upon him, than upon a <hi>dead man</hi> that hath neither <hi>ſenſe</hi> nor <hi>motion,</hi> nor <hi>life</hi> in him: But yet, in the mean while, though his <hi>heart</hi> be <hi>dead</hi> to this world world and all the <hi>fine toyes</hi> and <hi>trifles</hi> of it, ſo as all the <hi>wealth, riches, gauderies,</hi> and <hi>glories</hi> thereof, be <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> to him, yet he is <hi>ſo wiſe,</hi> as to minde the things of the <hi>other world;</hi> theſe as he <hi>highly prizeth</hi> and <hi>values</hi> them, at their <hi>juſt rate,</hi> ſo he <hi>earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeeks</hi> after them: His <hi>whole buſineſs</hi> lies here, namely, <hi>by patient continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in well-doing, to ſeek for glory, honour, immortality, eternal Life.</hi> (<hi>Rom.</hi> 2.7.) and this being the trade hee drives, every <hi>ſtep</hi> he treads is <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven,</hi> and to a being made <hi>meet</hi> for the enjoyment of it. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe,</hi>
                     <pb n="113" facs="tcp:152194:63"/>an unregenerate perſon takes <hi>quite</hi> another courſe, he is all for <hi>earth,</hi> and for <hi>earthly</hi> things; all for, either the <hi>profits</hi> of the world, if his heart be <hi>choaked with covetous cares and thoughts;</hi> or for the <hi>pleaſures</hi> of the world, if he be a <hi>bruitiſh ſenſualist;</hi> or for the <hi>honours, dignities,</hi> and <hi>high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>places</hi> of the world, if he be of a <hi>lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and <hi>proud Spirit:</hi> As for the <hi>injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of God, or the <hi>ſaving</hi> of his ſoul, they are matters <hi>too ſerious</hi> for him to minde; <hi>mundus cum ſuis fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volis,</hi> the frivolous World is his <hi>Idol,</hi> and that he will <hi>adore,</hi> though with the <hi>loſſe</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> it ſelf, and all the <hi>bliſſes</hi> thereof for ever, which being ſo, may we not conclude, that every <hi>ſtep</hi> he treads is <hi>towards Hell,</hi> and that he is <hi>ripening</hi> apace for it?</p>
                  <p>Thus we ſee what a <hi>vaſt difference</hi> there is, between a <hi>regenerate</hi> perſon, and an <hi>unregenerate</hi> in their <hi>lives.</hi> Let us ſee now what the difference is in their <hi>deaths.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:152194:64"/>
                  <p> The <hi>regenerate</hi> perſon, (1.) Hath no <hi>ſtings,</hi> nor <hi>gaulings</hi> of Conſcience his <hi>main worke</hi> is done, when he comes to lye upon his <hi>dying-Bed.</hi> It hath been his <hi>every daies work</hi> to ſet things <hi>right,</hi> and to keep them <hi>ſo,</hi> (to the utmoſt of his endeavour) betwixt God and him, to get, and grow up into an <hi>intire friendſhip</hi> with him, and ſtill to call himſelf to an <hi>account</hi> for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing that might <hi>offend,</hi> and with all ſpeed to <hi>hasten</hi> to the <hi>blood of ſprinkling, to be waſhed and cleanſed:</hi> he would never be at reſt, ſo long as <hi>guilt</hi> remained upon his <hi>own heart,</hi> or one <hi>frown</hi> in the <hi>face of God</hi> towards him. But <hi>this</hi> the <hi>unregenerate</hi> perſon never did, nor would ever by any means be <hi>perſwaded</hi> to it; <hi>ſelf-Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, ſelf-Reflexion,</hi> and <hi>ſelf-Judging,</hi> were Duties which he was alwaies a <hi>ſtranger</hi> to, theſe were works for an <hi>awakened,</hi> and a <hi>tender</hi> Conſcience, which he never had, nor <hi>deſired</hi> to have; and ſo now, judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:152194:64"/>is given up, happily, <hi>to a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience paſt feeling,</hi> and that cannot be ſenſible of any thing. (2.) In caſe a <hi>regenerate,</hi> and <hi>holy</hi> perſon ſhould be under ſome <hi>little clouds</hi> for a <hi>while,</hi> and through the <hi>malice</hi> of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> by Divine permiſſion, be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what <hi>damped</hi> in his inward <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>comfort,</hi> when hee is about his laſt work of dying, yet, as hath been ſaid, there is <hi>no just reaſon</hi> why it ſhould be thus with him; and 'tis <hi>very rare,</hi> that any <hi>good man</hi> or <hi>woman</hi> is <hi>long</hi> vexed thus; but to be ſure, the <hi>ſtorm ends at laſt,</hi> and the <hi>reſt</hi> of their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage is uſually under a <hi>pleaſant</hi> and <hi>fair</hi> gale, God himſelf as I may ſo ſay, <hi>ſitting at the sterne,</hi> and the holy Angels <hi>ſpreading the Sails:</hi> And Oh then! the <hi>calmneſs</hi> of their mindes! the <hi>ſerenity</hi> of their peace! the <hi>inward quiet</hi> of their ſouls, how <hi>great</hi> is it! How is not Death then <hi>at all dreadful!</hi> but rather a <hi>welcome Meſſenger,</hi> which they now look for, and <hi>wonder</hi> that
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:152194:65"/>his Chariot wheels move <hi>no faſter!</hi> which <hi>bleſſed</hi> repoſe being now caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, after their <hi>buffetings</hi> and <hi>combates</hi> with Satan, on a ſudden, they breathe forth their <hi>perfumed</hi> breath, and ſo <hi>fall aſleep in Jeſus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But alas! How <hi>far otherwiſe</hi> is it with a <hi>wicked unregenerate</hi> man, when he comes to this <hi>dying worke?</hi> For, if his Conſcience be not ſo far <hi>ſeared, blinded,</hi> and left <hi>judicially inſenſible,</hi> as was but even now mentioned; but is let <hi>looſe</hi> upon him, and <hi>inabled</hi> by the God of Conſcience, to <hi>charge</hi> him, and <hi>accuſe</hi> him <hi>home:</hi> If it calls <hi>all his ſins</hi> to remembrance, and <hi>ſets them in order before him</hi> (a work, which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times God, to ſhew his Power, will aſſiſt this or that wicked mans Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in as himſelf ſpeaks <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.21.) I ſay when once Conſcience <hi>acts this</hi> part upon ſome <hi>obſtinate</hi> and <hi>impenitent</hi> wretch, and hath a <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion</hi> ſo to do. Oh then! the <hi>roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings! the yellings!</hi> the <hi>howlings,</hi> of
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:152194:65"/>ſuch a Conſcience! How then doth death come with <hi>all its stings!</hi> how doth Hell fire <hi>flaſh</hi> in his face with <hi>all its flames!</hi> And how doth the <hi>Devil</hi> himſelf, as 'twere <hi>haunt</hi> and <hi>affright</hi> him with <hi>all his Feinds?</hi> Oh now the <hi>horrors,</hi> the <hi>terrors,</hi> the <hi>ſoul-ſinking o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-whelming</hi> dreads that are upon him! may not his Name bee now changed into <hi>magor-miſſabib, fear round about?</hi> He that before ſeemed to have <hi>no ſuch power, faculty,</hi> or <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple</hi> of Conſcience in him, (call it what you will) no ſuch <hi>vicegerency</hi> of the Divine Majeſty, <hi>for what is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, but Gods Vicegerent?</hi>) Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold now he findes it <hi>much otherwiſe:</hi> he now <hi>experiments</hi> the truth of thoſe words in <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.27. <hi>The Spirit of a man is the candle of the Lord, ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the inward parts of the Belly;</hi> and 'tis not onely a <hi>ſhining,</hi> but a <hi>burning</hi> Candle too, that <hi>kindles wrath,</hi> as wel as <hi>diſcovers ſin:</hi> and can you imagin it poſſible for <hi>ſuch tormented ones,</hi> as
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:152194:66"/>this poor miſerable <hi>ſelf-condemned</hi> man, is not to be afraid to dye? Doubtleſs they are <hi>afraid,</hi> and <hi>afraid</hi> to ſuch a <hi>degree,</hi> as is not eaſie to be expreſſed; and yet whilſt they live <hi>in this manner,</hi> is not their very <hi>life</hi> a <hi>burthen</hi> to them, and a <hi>ſore torment?</hi> are not theſe the men of whom <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctetus</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>apud Stob. c.</hi> 120. (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.) a certain wonderful ſort of men, that are weary of life, and yet have no minde to dye, or of whom <hi>Seneca</hi> ſpeaks in his fourth Epiſt; <hi>Inter mortis metum &amp; vitae tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta miſeri fluctuant, &amp; vivere no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunt, &amp; mori neſciunt,</hi> that are miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably toſſed betwixt the fear of <hi>Death,</hi> and the torments of <hi>Life;</hi> have no deſire to live, and yet know not how to dye? And the ſame <hi>Seneca</hi> again, Epiſt. 101. <hi>Invenitur qui malit inter ſupplicia-tabeſcere &amp; perire membra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim, &amp; toties per stillicidia amittere animam quam ſemel exhalare? Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitur
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:152194:66"/>qui velit trahere animam tot tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta tracturam? Uſque adeonè mori miſerum eſt? Eſt tanti habere animam, ut agam?</hi> Would one think that the man ſhould be found upon earth, that would rather waſte away by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees among grievous ſufferings, be content to rot in pieces one member after another, and let his ſoul go out, as 'twere by drops, rather than to ſend it out all together, at one ſingle groan? That any man ſhould bee found that would endure the length<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening out of his life under ſo many torments? Is death ſo miſerable a thing, to be thus affrighted at it? Yea and is life too, of ſo great value, as to be thus defired? The like paſſage we finde in <hi>Cyprian</hi> alſo (in his Book <hi>de Mortal.</hi>) concerning <hi>ſome</hi> in his age; <hi>Pati non vultis, exire timetis, quid faciam vobis?</hi> Ye are unwilling to live under your ſufferings, and yet ye are unwilling to dye, what ſhall I do unto you? Or, how ſhall I <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> you?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="exhortation">
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:152194:67"/>
                  <head>Second Uſe for Exhortation.</head>
                  <p>TO <hi>good</hi> and <hi>bad;</hi> to <hi>regenerate,</hi> and <hi>unregenerate.</hi> Firſt to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate, to whom (would they could all hear it) I would make it my moſt <hi>earneſt requeſt</hi> that they would do <hi>five</hi> things. 1. Sit down and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think</hi> themſelves, that they would go into their <hi>retirements,</hi> though 'twere, but for <hi>one half hour</hi> in a day, and <hi>ſeriouſly conſider,</hi> what their <hi>condition</hi> is, how <hi>doleful! diſmal! dangerous!</hi> How <hi>angry</hi> God is with them, and that <hi>continually</hi> and <hi>unappeaſedly,</hi> whilſt they <hi>remain impenitent</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing</hi> in this their unregenerate ſtate! That they would conſider, <hi>what vengeance hangs over their heads,</hi> hourly, and that if they live and dye. Thus, there can be <hi>no poſsible hope</hi> of good for them. That, if ſtill they remain <hi>fearleſs,</hi> and <hi>careleſs</hi> of God, and will not hearken to his <hi>calls</hi> and
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:152194:67"/>
                     <hi>counſels,</hi> now in their life time, when <hi>pangs of death</hi> come upon them, and they then <hi>cry out for mercy,</hi> miſerably <hi>roaring</hi> in the very <hi>anguiſh</hi> of their ſoul, God will be <hi>ſo far</hi> from hearing them (who when time was would not hear him) that <hi>he will laugh at their calamity, and mock when their fear comes, Prov.</hi> 1.24.-33. (2.) That hereupon they would <hi>pitty</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and be no longer <hi>cruel</hi> to their <hi>own precious ſouls;</hi> that they would no more neglect their <hi>own ſalvation,</hi> the <hi>great ſalvation</hi> offered them in the Goſpel: For how much <hi>ſorer puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> than ordinary, muſt not they look for, <hi>who neglect ſo great ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Heb.</hi> 2.3. (3.) That they would <hi>ſuffer the words of Exhortation, inſtruction, and counſel</hi> from plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dealing friends, and ſuch as have a <hi>true pity</hi> for them, whether they have any pity for themſelves or not; (4.) That they would be prevailed with to <hi>break off</hi> from their <hi>evil company,</hi> and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:152194:68"/>fall in with the Lords <hi>precious people;</hi> give <hi>attendance</hi> upon his <hi>holy Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> that of <hi>Preaching, eſpecially,</hi> which is a <hi>converting Ordinance,</hi> and where God is preſent with it, will ſoon make a <hi>change upon</hi> the moſt <hi>perverſe</hi> ſinner in the world. (5.) That they will <hi>delay no longer,</hi> but <hi>haſten</hi> to do this, with <hi>all ſpeed,</hi> leaſt the <hi>door</hi> of <hi>Mercy</hi> be <hi>ſhut</hi> upon them, and the <hi>opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> paſt before they are aware of it.</p>
                  <p>To the <hi>regenerate,</hi> even all the <hi>true Saints</hi> and Servants of the <hi>high God;</hi> My Exhortation to <hi>them</hi> is two-fold: Firſt more General, then more Particularly to ſome of them.</p>
                  <p>My <hi>General Exhortation</hi> to all, is, unto three things. (1.) To <hi>pity</hi> all ſuch as ſtill <hi>abide</hi> in their <hi>unregenerate eſtate.</hi> Though they <hi>hate</hi> you, yet do you <hi>pity</hi> them, yea, and <hi>pray</hi> for them, <hi>watch</hi> for all <hi>opportunity</hi> of doing <hi>good</hi> to their ſouls, give them the <hi>exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of an holy life,</hi> and every way do
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:152194:68"/>your <hi>utmoſt</hi> if it be poſſible, <hi>to pluck them as fire-brands out of the devouring flames.</hi> (2.) Bleſſe God for your <hi>own most rich</hi> and <hi>unſpeakable</hi> Mercy, that your ſelves are not in the <hi>ſame caſe</hi> with them. That he hath made ſuch a <hi>vaſt difference</hi> between you: What are you <hi>naturally</hi> better than they? Were not <hi>both hewed out of the ſame Rock?</hi> And whence doth the difference riſe? Is it not <hi>altogether from free-Grace?</hi> Yes verily, alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether from free Grace; <hi>Not by works of Righteouſneſs, which we had done,</hi> (ſaies the Apoſtle <hi>Titus</hi> 2.5.) <hi>But through his Mercy he ſaved us, by the waſhing of Regeneration.</hi> Oh then be <hi>thankful.</hi> For what <hi>greater</hi> thing than this, <hi>can God himſelf</hi> do for you than he hath done, in making <hi>ſuch a change</hi> upon you. (3.) Walk <hi>worthy</hi> of all this <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs.</hi> Let God have <hi>ſomething</hi> from you <hi>anſwerable</hi> to his <hi>kindneſs,</hi> and this his <hi>diſtinguiſhing</hi> love to you; and <hi>from you of all others,</hi>
                     <pb n="124" facs="tcp:152194:69"/>from whom he hath <hi>removed</hi> the <hi>fears</hi> of Death, ſo that 'tis <hi>no way dreadful</hi> to you, but come when it will come, it ſhall be <hi>welcome</hi> to you.</p>
                  <p>But as for <hi>ſuch</hi> of you, among the <hi>Lords People,</hi> as happily may not bee <hi>quite gotten over</hi> theſe fears, and yet may bee truely willing <hi>to bee with Christ,</hi> and thereupon could even wiſh that you had <hi>once ſhot this Gulf of Death;</hi> Let me ſpeak to you more <hi>particularly,</hi> and entreat you, (1.) That you would <hi>ſeriouſly conſider,</hi> how <hi>uncomely,</hi> at leaſt, if not a kinde of <hi>inconſiſtent</hi> thing it is, for thoſe that <hi>pretend</hi> for Heaven, and do, in good <hi>earneſt</hi> ſet their faces thither-ward, to <hi>be afraid of Death?</hi> Even an <hi>Heathen</hi> could ſay, I mean <hi>Seneca</hi> (Epiſt. 24.) <hi>Confirmandus eſt animus, vel ad mortis, vel ad vitae patientiam,</hi> the minde ought to be armed with patience, as well for Death, as for Life. The <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings,</hi> which we may meet with in <hi>both,</hi> may call for it, and what he far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:152194:69"/>ſaith, (Epiſt. 95.) is too true. <hi>Interdum obnixè petimus, quod oblatum recuſaremus; multa videri volumus velle, ſed nolumus, aliud optamus, &amp; verum ne Diis quidem dicimus.</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times that which we earneſtly wiſh for ('tis of death he ſpeaks) when 'tis offered us, we refuſe; wee ſeem to will many things, which yet we again reject, and deſire ſomething elſe in the room of it, and ſo ſpeak not the truth even to God himſelf: would not one <hi>wonder,</hi> that a <hi>poor Heathen</hi> ſhould ſpeak thus? <hi>Cyprian</hi> (in his Book <hi>De Mortal.</hi>) utters himſelf al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in the ſame manner, and with great elegancy, <hi>Quam praepoſterum eſt, quamque perverſum, &amp; cum Dei voluntatem fieri poſtulemus, quando evocat nos, &amp; accerſit de hoc mundo, non ſtatim voluntatis ejus imperio pareamus, hoc nitimur &amp; reluctamur, &amp; pervica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium more ſervorum, ad conſpectum Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, cum triſtitia &amp; maerore perduci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, non obſequio voluntatis. Et volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:152194:70"/>ab eo praemiis caeleſtibus honorari, ad quem venimus inviti.</hi> How prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous and perverſe a thing is it, that we pray to God that his will may bee done, and yet when he calls us hence, and ſends for us out of this world, we do not preſently obey his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign will, but oppoſe it, ſtruggle againſt it, and like untoward Servants are afraid to appear in the preſence of our Lord? With ſorrow and grief we are dragged to him, rather than go to him in obedience to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: We go unwillingly to him, and yet deſire to be honoured by his Heavenly rewards: <hi>And then a little after, Quid rogamus &amp; petimus ut ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniat regnum caelorum, ſi captivitas nos terrena delectat? Quid precibus frequenter iteratis rogamus, &amp; poſcimus ut acceleret dies regni, ſi majora deſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, &amp; vota potiora ſunt ſervire iſthic Diabolo, quam regnare cum Chriſto?</hi> Why do we pray and deſire that the Kingdome of Heaven may come, if
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:152194:70"/>we be ſtill in love with our Earthly captivity? Why do we ſo frequently deſire that that day may haſten, if we have greater deſires, and do more ſtrongly wiſh, rather to abide here, in the Devils Service, than to Reign with Chriſt? <hi>thus we ſee, even many ages ſince,</hi> not onely among <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> but among <hi>Heathens,</hi> what a kinde of <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> they reckoned it to be, to ſeem to <hi>long for Heaven, and an immortal ſtate,</hi> and yet when the time comes for ſuch a <hi>bleſſed change,</hi> to be <hi>loath</hi> to go to it. <hi>Una iſta catena, amor vitae, quàm nos alligatos tenet?</hi> (<hi>Sen.</hi> Epiſt. 26.) How doth that one chain, the love of life hold us here as Priſoners, ſaies <hi>Seneca?</hi> Whoever thou art then that reckoneſt thy ſelf a <hi>true Chriſtian,</hi> and a <hi>Believer,</hi> let theſe paſſages even of an <hi>Heathen</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect thee, and hereafter cauſe thee to <hi>bluſh</hi> for <hi>ſhame,</hi> at thine own fears. But,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> That thou maiſt the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:152194:71"/>get over theſe thy fears, and be the <hi>more ready</hi> with <hi>chearfulneſs</hi> to welcome Death when it comes, do theſe three things.</p>
                  <p n="1">(1.) Be every day <hi>preparing to dye,</hi> and putting thy ſelf into a <hi>poſture</hi> for it: among the many <hi>excellent</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages that <hi>Seneca</hi> hath about this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, even through moſt of his works, there are <hi>two</hi> of them worthy to bee written <hi>in letters of Gold;</hi> One is in his Book <hi>de brev. vitae c.</hi> 7. <hi>Vivere totâ vitâ diſcendum eſt, &amp; quod magis fortaſſe miraberis, totâ vitâ diſcendum eſt mori:</hi> A man all his life time had need be learning to live, and which perhaps thou wilt more marvel at, he muſt be all his life-time learning to dye too. <hi>The other is in his</hi> 30th. Epiſt. <hi>Magna res eſt, &amp; diu diſcenda, cum adventat hora illa inevitablis, aequo animo exire.</hi> It is a great thing, and alwaies to be learned, that when that inevitable hour (of death) comes, we may depart this life with a well-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:152194:71"/>minde, <hi>which</hi> who can do, but he that hath ſet all things <hi>right,</hi> and ſo having attained to a <hi>meetneſs</hi> to partake of the inheritance of the Saints hath left nothing <hi>farther to be done,</hi> in order to the getting into the <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> of it, but to <hi>breathe forth his last breath.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">(2.) <hi>Meditate much upon death,</hi> and that every day, that ſo you may thereby grow <hi>familiar</hi> with it. This the Holy Ghoſt calls the <hi>wiſdome</hi> of man, and that which every <hi>good man</hi> prayes that he may be enabled to do. <hi>Moſes himſelf</hi> did ſo (Pſalm 99.12.) <hi>ſo teach us to number our dayes,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that we may apply our hearts unto wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome;</hi> and whoever hath any of <hi>that Spirit</hi> which moved in him will do the <hi>like.</hi> When I read that paſſage of <hi>Plato apud Plut. de placit Philoſoph.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, They beſt act the true Philoſophers, that are moſt ſollicitous about death: I am apt to think ſure hee had read
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:152194:72"/>this prayer of <hi>Moſes;</hi> yet among all that ſort of <hi>antient Writers,</hi> I finde <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> who lived in the time of the <hi>ſiege</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> by the <hi>Caldean Army,</hi> and ſo in the Prophet <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah's</hi> daies, at leaſt two hundred years before <hi>Plato,</hi> and ſo (according to our <hi>learned Uſher</hi>'s account) ſome ſix hundred and forty years before <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Nativity,</hi> was the <hi>firſt</hi> that called <hi>Phyloſophy the Meditation of Death;</hi> after whom <hi>Socrates</hi> alſo and many others had the <hi>like</hi> expreſſions which makes me think, had <hi>theſe,</hi> and the reſt of thoſe <hi>famous men,</hi> even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Heathen,</hi> that knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the true God, been <hi>alive in our daies,</hi> and been bleſſed with <hi>ſuch a ſaving</hi> light of the Goſpel, as ſome few are, what <hi>rare inſtances</hi> would they have been? How would they have out-ſtripped us in their <hi>affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> and <hi>deſires</hi> Heaven-ward! and in their <hi>Maſteries</hi> over Death and the <hi>fear</hi> of it? How would they have
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:152194:72"/>made it their <hi>great buſineſs</hi> to <hi>converſe</hi> with Death, even as much as we are wont to do with our <hi>intireſt friends!</hi> They which made <hi>Phyloſophy</hi> chiefly to conſiſt in the <hi>Meditation of death,</hi> would have made the <hi>Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> to conſiſt in it <hi>much more.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">(3.) <hi>Store your ſelves with paſſages from the holy Scriptures,</hi> repleniſh your minde with the <hi>great and precious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,</hi> let Divine Truths, and the Heavenly Sentences thereof <hi>dwell in you richly in all Spiritual Wiſdome and Underſtanding,</hi> that ſo when you lie upon your <hi>Sick,</hi> or (it may be) your <hi>Dying-Beds,</hi> you may have them ſo <hi>fixed</hi> in your <hi>heads</hi> and <hi>hearts,</hi> that they may afford <hi>much ſweet</hi> and <hi>preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous matter</hi> unto your thoughts: If you make <hi>this</hi> a <hi>good part,</hi> not onely of your <hi>buſineſs,</hi> but of your <hi>delight</hi> too, in your <hi>life-time,</hi> may you not <hi>well hope</hi> and <hi>expect,</hi> that when <hi>Death comes,</hi> the Holy Ghoſt will <hi>bring things, to your remembrance,</hi> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:152194:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <hi>ſuch Cordials</hi> from thence to you, as ſhall <hi>marvellouſly comfort</hi> and <hi>refreſh you,</hi> even when the <hi>pangs</hi> of death it ſelf ſhall bee upon you? <hi>Many</hi> and <hi>pleaſant</hi> are the <hi>ſtories</hi> that might here be told, of the <hi>great</hi> and <hi>powerful con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations,</hi> that have come in upon <hi>Dying Saints,</hi> from <hi>this</hi> or <hi>that</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, or other Paſſage of Scripture, <hi>upon the wings whereof, they have gone up in Triumph to Heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152194:73"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
